<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Ayurvedic</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="nav_header_title">Ayurvedic</string>
   <!-- <string name="nav_header_subtitle">android.studio@android.com</string>-->
    <string name="nav_header_desc">Navigation header</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Help</string>

    <string name="menu_home">Home</string>
    <string name="menu_gallery">Gallery</string>
    <string name="menu_slideshow">Slideshow</string>
    <string name="menu_tools">Tools</string>
    <string name="menu_share">Share</string>
    <string name="menu_send">Rate us</string>
    <string name="menu_about">About us</string>

    <string name="alovera">"ALovera ,What are the benefits of aloe vera?"</string>
    <string name="tusli">"Tusli , The Health Benefits of Holy Basil"</string>
    <string name="triphala">"Top 20 Benefits of Triphala Churna (Powder)"</string>
    <string name="ashoka">"10 AMAZING Uses Of Ashoka Tree Will Leave You Shellshocked!"</string>
    <string name="garlic">"8 Surprising Health Benefits of Garlic "</string>
    <string name="chamomile">"13 Benefits Of Chamomile Tea For Skin, Hair And Overall Health: Drink Up!"</string>
    <string name="ginger">"8 Incredible Health Benefits of Ginger"</string>
    <string name="ginseng">"8 Amazing Benefits of Ginseng"</string>
    <string name="nutmeg">"14 Amazing Benefits of Nutmeg"</string>
    <string name="chocolate">"8 Healthy Reasons to Eat Dark Chocolate"</string>
    <string name="gotucola">"What are the benefits of gotu kola?"</string>
    <string name ="ashwagandha">"5 healthy benefits of Ashwagandha"</string>
    <string name="bitter_melon">"10 Benefits of Bitter Melon That Makes It Even More Worth Eating"</string>
    <string name="turmeric">"10 Proven Health Benefits of Turmeric Curcumin Supplements"</string>
    <string name="trikatu">"10 Health Benefits Of Trikatu, The Potent Trinity "</string>

    <string name="cardamom">"15 Health Benefits Of Cardamom"</string>

    <string name="mulethi">"Mulethi (Liquorice Root) Benefits: From Digestion to Immunity and More!"</string>

    <string name="majistha">"11 Health Benefits Of Manjistha You Should Tap Into"</string>
    <string name="amalaki">"5 Wonder Benefits Of Amalaki (Gooseberry,Nellikka)"</string>
    <string name="brahmi">"The Amazing Benefits of Brahmi (Bacopa Monnieri)"</string>
    <string name="brahmi_details">"Brahmi (Bacopa monnieri) is a very common household name, thrown around by elders who stand by ayurvedic medicine staunchly. It is not uncommon for them to advise you to consume Brahmi in some way or the other, either in raw form or in the form of some capsule or so. Brahmi benefits are aplenty and quite noticeable. In fact it is even believed to boost your memory and hone your intellect if consumed daily. It is said that the Vedic scholars used to consume this herb to facilitate the memorization of long and intricate passages of hymns, religious texts and scriptures.  This herb does not have any particular scent and is known by a variety of names like water hyssop, herb of grace or the Indian pennywort. It usually can be found growing near marshy lands, even in water, (which is why it’s a popular choice as an aquarium plant) and also in brackish conditions.

Brahmi gets its name from the powerful creator of the world, according to the Hindu scriptures, Brahma. This plant can be found growing in the wetlands of southern and Eastern India, and in various places around the world, namely Australia, Europe, Africa, Asia, and also in North and South America.
Brahmi benefits people undergoing treatment for epilepsy, rheumatism, asthma, joint pain and swelling, unblocking the chest cavity, even mental retardation and hoarseness of voice. Thus, it is an essential herb that you should know about as the Brahmi benefits the general health of the body in a number of ways. Here are eleven amazing facts that you should know about Brahmi:




1) Brahmi Benefits the Brain:

An active compound in Brahmi is bacosides. It has been shown to stave off mental degradation that comes with age. It has also positively slowed down the effects of Alzheimer’s on the brain by helping in the regeneration of brain tissues and cells. The presence of amyloid is what causes Alzheimer’s and the bacosides in Brahmi helps reduce its effect on the human brain. Bacosides also protects the nervous system from harm and helps in the betterment of the general functioning of the neurons.



2) Brahmi Benefits the Liver:

Since the liver is the biggest agent of detoxification of the body, the compounds in Brahmi benefits the liver in this aspect. It helps by aiding the liver in its conversion of toxins into harmless ones and into waste products. When liver function is impaired due to toxin build up in the body and the release of nutrients into the bloodstream is stalled, it can lead to complications in proper body functions. Brahmi helps the liver work properly and it is natural and effective without harmful side effects.



3) Brahmi Benefits Memory:

Studies have shown that Brahmi helps in heightening cognitive performances and in a recent experiment in a placebo-controlled environment involving 24 people it was learnt that Brahmi benefits the cognitive performance of the brain, blurry eye sight, and memory by increasing the power of retention.




4) Brahmi Benefits Dealing with Hair Related Problems:

Brahmi treats a range of hair related troubles. Massaging of hot Brahmi oil is beneficial for the scalp, as it enriched with bio-chemical compounds that act as anti-oxidants. The oil helps stimulate the hair follicles resulting in thick hair growth, elimination of dandruff and itchy scalp and also helps baldness and alopecia.




5) Brahmi Benefits Dealing with Opioid Addiction:

Pain medication while effective, also has an addictive side to it and sometimes you may tend to feel a dependency towards them. Brahmi rich in bacosides actually helps deal with it by eliminating the tendency to enjoy the high that comes from pain medication whereas enhancing its function in dealing with the pain. It also acts as a protective cushion around organs that might be prone to damage from use or overuse of opioids and pain medication.




6) Brahmi Benefit Dealing with Mental Health:

Brahmi promotes mental clarity. Nitric oxide, which is another major active compound in Brahmi, helps with concentration, mental alertness, helps to deal with withdrawal symptoms from opioids that could cause depression, and facilitates the proper functioning of the brain.




7) Brahmi Benefits Dealing with Inflammation:

Brahmi reduces inflammation and swelling of the brain which is caused by the response of the autoimmune system of the body. Not only does Brahmi help in reducing the swelling, itchiness and redness of the brain surface but also anywhere on the body, Brahmi will effectively heal it and it’s completely natural.




8) Brahmi Benefits Flushing out of Toxins from the Body:

Brahmi protects the neural system from neurotoxins such as aluminium, morphine and cigarette smoke thereby helping to flush the body of toxic deposits. It also guards against oxidative stress.




9) Brahmi Benefits Stress Reduction:

Stress is caused due to an overabundance of the cortisol hormone. Brahmi reduces the effect of the cortisol hormone by becoming an adaptogen and thereby reliving you of stress and improving your mood.




10) Brahmi Benefits the Treatment of Epilepsy:

While bacopa is used to treat neurological problems, as well as for the enhancement of cognitive functions, its usefulness can be extended in helping to treat other neurological problems such as epilepsy when consumed along with vacha. The healing properties of bacosides include healing of damaged neurons and slowing down of neuro-degeneration as well as boosting neuro-transmission within brain cells.



11) Brahmi Benefits the Treatment of Insomnia:

Sleeping disorders are a massive issue that people everywhere have to deal with. Some people overwork themselves to feel sleepy at night but that is never a foolproof method. Chances are if you suffer from insomnia you are suffering from a range of other problems as well like depression, anxiety, stress and tiredness. Massaging hot Brahmi oil can help deal with all these secondary problems and the root of them, insomnia. It reduces stress and calms you down enough to help you fall into a comfortable sleep pattern. It even helps, if your child is a hyperactive one, then the massaging of Brahmi oil proves beneficial.
        "</string>

    <string name="amalaki_details">"What is Amalaki ?

Amalaki is a tree that grows throughout Asia that bears a lemon-sized fruit for several months out of the year. The fruit has a bitter taste and so is not usually eaten on its own, but rather prepared as part of a meal or condensed into supplement form. For the purposes of use as an herbal supplement, the fruit is dried and then ground into a powder. Amalaki has different names depending on where it is grown and thus is also known as:

    Amla
    Indian gooseberry
    Nellikka


5 Wonder benefits of amalaki

1. Amalaki for hair: The fruit juice is used for a hair-wash to prevent premature greying and hair fall. It imparts a beautiful lustre and smooth the hair.


2. Skin: Gooseberry juice exfoliates and cleanses your skin, by removing the dead cells. You can add gooseberry  juice to your daily diet, to keep your skin clean from within. You can also apply gooseberry  juice on your face, and leave it undisturbed for 30 minutes. After that, wash it off with lukewarm water. If you have a sensitive skin, then dilute the juice with water rather than direct application.


3. Weight Loss: The dry powder massage (Udgharshana) with triphalapowder help to reduce the subcutaneous fats in obesity.


4. Eyesight: Daily eyewash with triphala-water improves the eyesight. It can make your eyesight better and helps you to stay away from vision problem for a quite long time. It is enriched with vitamin C which is extremely important for better eye vision. So, you can eat one single amla everyday and it can make your eyes better. If you have kids then make them eat one half amla everyday.


5. Body lustre: The mix of the paste of rind of Haritaki fruit and Gooseberry, along with roots of Jatamansi when applied before bathing, helps to make the body fragrant and lustrous.


How to Use Amla

Because taste plays such an important role in the digestive process and signals the body to initiate its own supportive mechanisms, Ayurveda traditionally recommends tasting herbs. Amla can be taken internally in four forms: a powder, a tablet, a liquid extract, or in a jam such as chyavanprash.
        "</string>

    <string name="manjistha_details">"Health Benefits Of Manjistha

    Improves skin tone
    Treats eczema
    Counters stress
    Protects the liver
    Counters kidney damage


Manjistha has anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties. It treats allergies, acne, eczema, and psoriasis and can improve your complexion. It can help you deal with stress and improve memory and learning ability. Manjistha also boosts wound healing, protects your kidney, liver, and immune system against toxins, and helps fight cancer.

Manjistha, Indian maddar, or Rubia cordifolia has a stellar reputation in traditional medicine, featuring in a range of herbal formulations as well as cosmetic preparations. The stems, roots, and shoots of this perennial, prickly climber with a red bark find a place in many remedies, though the root is used most extensively. Compounds such as anthraquinones, bicyclic hexapeptides, quinones, and iridoids in manjistha are responsible for many of its beneficial properties. Here's what you should know about the health benefits of manjistha.



1. Improves Your Complexion

Manjistha forms a part of many ayurvedic formulations that are beneficial for your skin. It is part of manjisthadi tailam and kumkumadi tailam, which are applied to get a glowing complexion, and also in kanak tailam, which fights premature aging and wrinkles.1

In ayurveda, manjistha is described as having "varṇya" property, that is, it can improve your complexion and make it lustrous. Traditionally, powdered dry roots and stem of this plant are mixed with honey and applied to erase dark spots and give you an even-toned complexion. Studies show that manjistha might indeed have a skin lightening effect. A pigment known as melanin is responsible for your skin color - the more melanin you have, the darker your skin is. Excessive deposits of melanin also lead to tan, freckles, brown spots, and hyperpigmentation disorders like melasma. If an uneven skin tone or blemishes are an issue you are grappling with, manjistha may be able to help by reducing melanin levels. It does so by inhibiting an enzyme known as tyrosinase which plays an important part in the production of this pigment.2 3



2. Tackles Acne

Manjistha can help you get rid of those annoying zits. Traditionally, the powdered root is mixed with ghee, or the pulp of the whole plant is applied along with honey to treat acne. Research indicates that manjistha acts against bacteria such as Propionibacterium acne and Staphylococcus epidermidis which play a role in the development of pimples. Moreover, its antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties also help fight acne.4




3. Helps Heal Wounds And Relieve Pain

Manjistha poultices and pastes are used by ayurveda for a variety of skin problems and injuries and can tackle irritation, swelling, pain, and inflammation.5

Manjistha has been traditionally been used to heal cuts and wounds. An animal study that examined the scientific validity of this folk remedy found that applying a gel containing manjistha extract was able to significantly improve wound contracting ability, tissue regeneration, and wound closure. It could also bring about a reduction in the surface area of the wound. Researchers suggest that anthraquinones and tannins present in this medicinal plant may be responsible for its wound-healing action.6 Animal studies have also shown that oral administration of manjistha extract can ease pain and even ease fever associated with inflammation.7




4. Eases Eczema Symptoms

Eczema is a common skin condition which results in itchy reddened skin and oozing blisters. Ancient ayurvedic texts describe the use of manjistha to treat a skin disease named "vicharchika" which exhibits symptoms similar to eczema.8 And as it turns out, scientific research also indicates that this ancient ayurvedic remedy just might be able to ease eczema. One study that examined the impact of using an ointment containing manjistha for a period of 2 weeks on people with this condition found that it significantly improved symptoms. On average, they observed an improvement of 62.06% in the symptoms of this disorder, with some participants showing an improvement of 50% in just 4 days.9




5. Helps Deal With Psoriasis

Psoriasis is a skin disease that develops when skin cells get replaced more quickly than is normal, resulting in crusty, flaky red patches with silvery scales.10 This condition is linked to the excessive proliferation and abnormal differentiation of skin cells known keratinocytes. And manjistha may help deal with this condition. In vitro studies show that extracts from the roots have an antiproliferative effect on keratinocytes.11




6. Fights Oxidative Stress

Oxidative stress can take quite a toll on your health and contribute to a range of illnesses such as heart disease, cancer, arthritis, diabetes, and Alzheimer's disease. It develops when your immune system cannot neutralize all the free radicals generated inside your body. Free radicals are an inevitable byproduct of the conversion of food to energy in the body but it can also be formed by overexposure to toxins whether via refined or processed foods, tobacco, alcohol, or environmental pollutants.12

Manjistha is considered one of those rare herbs in ayurveda which has both soma (cooling) and agni (heating) properties.

While it is important to finetune your lifestyle and diet to keep free radicals in check, foods with antioxidant properties can help you fight the good fight. Manjistha is one such superfood that has potent antioxidant benefits and can scavenge free radicals. It also helps that it has anti-inflammatory properties, which can counter the effect of chronic inflammation, another immune response that can wreak havoc on your body. So go ahead and kill two birds with one with manjistha!13 14




7. Counters Stress

Animal studies have found that manjistha can act against chemically induced amnesia to improve memory as well as enhance learning ability. This ancient plant may be able to keep your mind sharp and protect you from succumbing to pressure and stress.15

From raising your blood pressure to causing backaches and acidity and worsening ulcers, stress can wreak havoc on your body. If you are feeling overwhelmed by daily pressures and it is taking a toll on your health, manjistha can help. One animal study found that it mitigated the effects of stress that was induced in rats by physically restraining them in a cold environment. Manjistha extract was found to significantly reduce acidity and ulcer index in these animals. But that's not all - it also had a beneficial effect on corticosterone and dopamine levels which play a role in your body's response to stress.16




8. Treats Allergies

Manjistha is an emmenagogue that can boost healthy and regular menstruation. It is also used in ayurveda to treat menstrual disorders.17 18

Manjistha has been used in ayurveda to fight allergies. Scientific research backs up its effectiveness. So how does it work? Research indicates that it can stabilize mast cells of the immune system and prevent the release of chemicals like histamine. This, in turn, reins in symptoms such as a running nose, itchy skin, or watery eyes which occur during an allergic reaction.19




9. Protects Your Liver

Your liver works tirelessly to eliminate toxins from your body. However, this hardworking organ can also be damaged by an assault of toxic substances ranging from smoke and environmental pollutants to some medicines. Manjistha might be able to exert a protective effect here. One animal study found that a compound known as rubiadin in manjistha was able to rebalance liver enzymes which were thrown out of whack due to exposure to the liver-damaging chemical carbon tetrachloride. It was also found to display a strong hepatoprotective effect and can be used to strengthen the liver.20 21




10. Boosts Kidney Function

Research shows that manjistha can protect your kidney against the harmful effects of toxic chemicals. One study looked at the impact of administering extracts of manjistha along with a drug used in chemotherapy that has a toxic effect on the kidney. Use of the chemotherapeutic agent resulted in elevated levels of creatinine and urea in the blood. These are waste products that are normally cleared by your kidney and high levels indicate a slowing down of the functioning of your kidneys.22 But treatment with manjistha extracts restored the elevated levels of creatinine and urea to normal.

This particular drug used in chemotherapy is thought to affect the kidneys due to its ability to deplete the antioxidant defense system. The free radical scavenging and antioxidant property of manjistha, in turn, may have a protective effect.23




11. Protects Against Kidney Stones

Kidney stones are quite common, with up to 2 in 20 women and 3 out of 20 men developing them at some point in their lives.24 They form when waste products turn to crystals, accumulate inside your kidney, and eventually develop into a stone-like lump. Manjistha might be able to prevent the formation of kidney stones to an extent. In one animal study, mice were administered ethylene glycol to induce kidney stones. But when these subjects were given an extract of the root of manjistha, it was able to modulate the excretion of minerals such as calcium, phosphate, and oxalate in the urine which are associated with the formation of stones.25




12. Boosts Immune System Function

We are surrounded by harmful pathogens that can cause infection and disease. While an active immune system protects and defends us from these, many factors can suppress your immune system and leave you vulnerable to disease. For instance, alcohol and the toxin lead nitrate have been known to have this effect. Animal studies show that manjistha can protect against the impairment of your immune system by these substances. In both these instances, the immunosuppression was found to occur due to oxidative stress and manjistha had a protective effect due to its potent antioxidant properties.26 27



13. Supports The Lymphatic System

Traditionally, manjistha has been used for purifying blood and helping with the proper functioning of the lymphatic system. The lymphatic system, an integral element of your immune system, transports fluids throughout your body. It is responsible for nourishing the tissues and draining waste and toxins from your body. Manjistha is believed to have a powerful influence on the lymphatic system, boosting its performance when it is sluggish or easing any lymphatic congestion that in turn can affect your whole body. Its benefits for the skin and female reproductive health are linked strongly to its impact on the lymphatic system.28 29



14. Fights Cancer

Manjistha has traditionally been used in ayurveda to treat uterine and ovarian cancers. And lab studies show that it can act against cancer cells in the colon, breast, and liver. It also has anti-tumor activity against various cancers such as myeloid leukemia and histolytic lymphoma.30 Some research indicates that cyclic hexapeptides and quinones present in this plant are responsible for its anticancer activity.31 However, do keep in mind that it's early days yet. More research is required in this area before manjistha can be effectively used to battle cancer. You can, however, check with your doctor whether manjistha can be beneficial as a supplementary treatment."</string>
    <string name="mulethi_details">"Some spices and herbs from our grandmothers' trove are so precious that till date they continue to be used in everyday home remedies. One such age-old herb that has been used for its exceptional health promoting properties is mulethi or liquorice, also spelt as licorice.

Some spices and herbs from our grandmothers' trove are so precious that till date they continue to be used in everyday home remedies. One such age-old herb that has been used for its exceptional health promoting properties is mulethi or liquorice, also spelt as licorice. A perennial herb that is found in various parts of Asia and Europe, mulethi has been used for centuries, especially in Ayurveda. Apart from medicines, it is widely used as a flavouring agent due to the natural sweetness the extract has.According to the book Healing Foods by DK Publishing, its anti-diabetic and anti-oxidant properties aid the treatment of metabolic syndrome. It supports liver health and is an antiseptic that helps to calm the stomach. It is also an expectorant and decongestant that can help fight respiratory infections. There is some evidence that liquorice in small amounts can be used to decrease sugar cravings. Moreover, it is also known to be beneficial in cases of low blood pressure.




1. Keeps the respiratory tract healthy

Chewing on mulethi sticks is an age-old remedy for a sore throat. It is due to its expectorant and bronchodilator properties that it can cure conditions like cough, bronchitis and also reduce the effects of chronic asthma. If you want to avoid chewing on mulethi sticks, you can mix ginger juice to mulethi tea in order to soothe asthma and bronchial infection.



2. Boosts immunity

Regular use of mulethi is known to boost immunity, thanks to the enzymes present in the root plant; it helps the body produce lymphocytes and macrophages that protect the body from microbes, pollutants, allergens and cells that cause autoimmune diseases, further keeping you away from infections and allergies and in turn boosting your immunity.



3. Boosts digestion

Mulethi has active compounds glycyrrhizin and carbenoxolone that are known to relieve constipation, stomach discomfort, heartburn, acidity and other stomach problems. It also acts as a mild laxative, playing an effective role in stimulating bowel movements.



4. Cures skin ailments

Mulethi is an emollient that helps maintain a healthy glowing skin. All you need to do is to add mulethi powder to rose water or milk depending on the type of your skin. This will help combat de-pigmentation and further soothe skin rashes.




5. Has anti-inflammatory properties

Liquorice has anti-inflammatory properties that may be able to treat chronic inflammatory diseases like arthritis. Its anti-oxidant properties also reduce the effects of free radicals causing pain and inflammation in the body.



6. Eases menopausal symptoms

The phytoestrogenic compounds in this herb help correct hormonal imbalance in the body to ease menopausal symptoms like hot flashes, insomnia, depression, mood swings, sweating, et al. A study published in the Iranian Journal of Pharmaceutical Research highlights its positive effect on menopausal hot flashes.

How can you use mulethi (liquorice)?

All you need to do is to boil the root to make a tea if you are feeling nauseous or are coming down with a cold. Liquorice tea is also good for maintaining dental health; try gargling with the cooled tea.


So go ahead and get your stock of mulethi ready for the cold days ahead and stay healthy."</string>
    <string name="cardamom_details">"

What is cardamom? Cardamom is native to the evergreen forests of India. This spice is commonly used in Indian cuisine, but it has also made its way into Ayurvedic medicine as a treatment for mouth ulcers, digestive problems, and even depression. Some of the health benefits of this peppery, citrusy spice are now making their way into modern studies. It’s well worth adding cardamom to your food for the flavor alone, but these health benefits are also something to consider whenever you break out the spices.


What Is Cardamom? Everything You Need to Know


Top 15 Cardamom Benefits


Using cardamom is no longer restricted to cooking Indian-inspired recipes and foods. In fact, cardamom pods, ground cardamom powder, cardamom essential oil, cardamom tea drinks, and other cardamom supplements are available on the market.

With the number of options growing, more and more people consider supplementing with cardamon for overall health. How exactly does the cardamom plant affect the body?

Before you decide to buy multiple pods of cardamom or packets of ground cardamom, check out these 15 health benefits of cardamom:



1. Ease Symptoms of Digestion Problems

​Cardamom is related to ginger and can be used in the same way to counteract digestive issues and problems. You can use it to combat nausea, acidity, bloating, gas, heartburn, loss of appetite, constipation, and much more.

Make a cup of cardamom tea and take small sips until your stomach calms down. If you don’t have cardamom tea, you can make your own digestive aid with edible cardamom oil or ground cardamom pods and some hot water.



2. Detoxify the Body and Remove Waste

This spice helps the body eliminate waste through the kidneys. This benefit is ideal for those who want to get rid of the toxins and chemicals from their body to speed up weight and fat loss.



3. Get Rid of Halitosis or Bad Breath

Chew on cardamom leaves! Cardamom is an aromatic spice that leaves a fresh, lingering scent in your mouth when you chew on it.

In India, they chew cardamom seeds or leaves after meals or whenever they need to freshen up their breath.




4. A Powerful Diuretic

Part of the reason cardamom is such a good detoxifier is thanks to its diuretic properties. It helps clean out the urinary tract, bladder, and kidneys, removing waste, salt, excess water, toxins, and combating infections, too.



5. Depression

Drinking relaxing and calming drinks infused with cardamom may be a way to improve one’s mood.

The science behind the antidepressant qualities of cardamom hasn’t been studied yet, but Ayurvedic medicine swears by the tea as a means to fight depression.

Also, it has a wonderful taste and relaxing scent that helps calm the senses. It might not be clinically proven to fight these mental illnesses, but you can still use them to help alleviate the symptoms.



6. Promotes Better Oral Health

Apart from helping with bad breath, cardamom is used for sore throats, mouth ulcers, and infections of the mouth and throat.

A recent study found that cardamom seeds and fruit could help improve oral health due to their anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties. The findings showed that the cardamom extract was effective in disrupting bacteria that can lead to gum disease or infections.




7. Prevent Cold and Flu Symptoms

This pungent spice may help prevent and relieve cold and flu symptoms. It’s also used for bronchitis and coughs.

In addition to being high in vitamins and minerals, the astringent properties of cardamom tea make it good for helping to fight off bacteria in the body. Drinking a warm cup of cardamom tea can be soothing on a sore throat and can even help suppress coughing.



8. May Reduce Risk of Developing Cancer

Animal studies are showing promise that cardamom protects against, inhibits growth, and even kills some cancers.

Keep in mind that there’s not enough proven studies showing that cardamom has any actual effect on the growth and development of cancer cells in humans. Don’t delay seeking medical advice if you suspect you’re at risk.





9. Regulates Blood Pressure

As a diuretic and fiber-rich spice, cardamom significantly lowers blood pressure. Exercising more, cutting back on sugar and adding more potassium to your diet and consuming less sodium can help keep your blood pressure steady.



10. Prevent Blood Clots

Cardamom prevents dangerous blood clots by preventing platelet aggregation and then sticking to the artery walls. In the long run, this may prove to be beneficial in preventing life-threatening clotting.



11. Acts as an Antioxidant
Woman enjoying the sun | Health Benefits Of Cardamom | what is cardamom | cardamom powder benefits

Many of the vitamins, phytonutrients, and essential oils in cardamom act as antioxidants, cleaning up free-radicals and resisting cellular aging. Getting rid of harmful free-radicals can balance blood sugar and cholesterol levels, improve blood pressure, and promote better overall health.



12. Combats Damaging Pathogens

The volatile essential oils in cardamom inhibit the growth of viruses, bacteria, fungus, and mold. In the long run, this can reduce your susceptibility to common diseases and illnesses.

Tip: To further increase immunity against diseases, take effective supplements such as Sunwarrior’s Immune Shield. Immune shield fights pathogens (bacterial, viral, fungal, parasitic) by interrupting the metabolic reactions and inhibiting cellular replication with ionic silver and trace minerals.



13. Has Anti-Inflammatory Properties

Like ginger and turmeric, its relative, cardamom has some anti-inflammatory properties that limit pain and swelling, especially in mucous membranes, mouth, and throat.


14. Gets Rid of Hiccups

Cardamom is an antispasmodic that can help get rid of hiccups. This also applies to other involuntary muscle spasms, like stomach and intestinal cramps.


15. Increase Libido as an Effective Aphrodisiac

Want to last longer and stronger in bed? Try supplementing with cardamom seeds!
Traditional medicine lists cardamom as a powerful aphrodisiac that can help with erectile dysfunction and impotence through better blood circulation."</string>

    <string name="trikatu_details">"Health Benefits Of Trikatu

Trikatu combines the goodness of black pepper, ginger, and long pepper to create a herbal remedy for digestive ailments, sluggish metabolism, obesity, and high cholesterol. Its immune-boosting effects and antimicrobial properties help you fight infections. Trikatu's ability to soothe colds, asthma, and bronchitis make it invaluable to those prone to seasonal allergies.



Health Benefits Of Trikatu

Trikatu is a herbal ayurvedic remedy that combines seemingly mundane larder ingredients to create a powerhouse remedy for everything from digestive problems to arthritis. This ancient blend makes the most of the warming effects of the spices it contains to rev up your metabolism, stimulate digestion, purge your body of toxins like mucus, and leaves you feeling like a new person. If that sounds promising, that's just the tip of the iceberg!

Trikatu Is A Combination Of Black Pepper, Long Pepper, And Ginger

A spice-laden ayurvedic formulation, the pungent trikatu elements can get your taste buds tingling while also doing wonders for your body in more ways than one. Made from a heady blend of black pepper or Piper nigrum, long pepper or Piper longum, and ginger or Zingiber officinale, it is prescribed by ayurvedic practitioners to treat multiple diseases courtesy the range of biological activities the piperine in the peppers has on mammals like us!1 The churna or powder of trikatu is said to be anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, digestive, pain-relieving, and expectorant - the main properties of the formulation that you will find tapped in the list of remedies to follow.2 Here's a more detailed look at its health benefits that you'd want to make the most of.




1. Improves Digestion And Detoxifies Your System

Trikatu churna is renowned for its ability to help you with digestion, so if you are having trouble in that department, look no further for much-needed relief. Long pepper helps rejuvenate your digestive system as does ginger, while the black pepper helps purge toxins. Together, these remedies combine in trikatu to improve food absorption, gastric function, appetite, and digestion overall. So if you are struggling with a sluggish digestive system, bloating, constipation, or other digestive problems like flatulence, you should consider trikatu.3




2. Improves Immunity And Fights Microbes

When it comes to fighting infections, trikatu can help on multiple fronts. It can not only boost immunity and enhance vitality but also has antibacterial properties.4 As one in-vitro study confirmed, it was able to counter bacterial strains that are common sources of many infections - the Staphylococcus aureus and Escherichia coli bacteria. Trikatu churna extract's action was even comparable to that of a popular mainstream antibiotic drug ampicillin.5

Studies also show that that trikatu churna has strong anthelmintic properties that help tackle parasites. The formulation has the potential to stimulate the immune system to counter parasitic activity in the body and expel them.6 Another study also confirmed its antifungal properties against fungal species like Mucor and Aspergillus niger that are implicated in some respiratory illnesses.7




3. Boosts Metabolism And Helps With Weight Loss

Trikatu may be just the ticket for someone with slow metabolism and can also help tackle weight problems or obesity. Ayurveda looks at trikatu as a heating remedy that can rev up your metabolism. As you've already seen, it helps boost digestion and expels toxins from your body. This stands you in good stead if you are obese or overweight or have a sluggish metabolism.8 Combine that with its ability to help fat metabolism in your liver and you have yourself a good weight loss aid.

In one study, over a duration of 3 months, taking 2 gm of trikatu churna twice daily could help bring about a drop in weight and body mass index (BMI) as well as hip circumference in people with dyslipidemia. Their lipid profiles also improved. Combining the churna with 20 gm of aloe vera pulp brought about an even greater reduction in both weight and BMI.9

Just remember, because trikatu is also an appetite stimulant, you might find yourself feeling hungrier when you first start to take it. Beat the hunger pangs with a healthy snack or a calorie-free herbal tea, watch your calorie intake, and you should be able to tap its benefits as a weight loss aid.




4. Helps Ease Respiratory Problems

Trikatu combined with an equal amount of honey and anise seeds is used as a remedy for springtime allergies or mucus in the respiratory system. The paste can be taken twice or thrice a day, a teaspoonful at a time.10

Trikatu acts as an expectorant and decongestant, clearing your lungs and air passages and helping you breathe normally when you have a cold, congestion, or other respiratory problems. Ayurveda believes that it helps eliminate "ama" or toxins and clears congestion in the form of mucus. It is also used to treat chest congestion and phlegm if you have bronchitis and asthma.11




5. Boosts Liver Function And Helps Treat Jaundice

Trikatu can also help those with liver diseases. In one animal study, trikatu was found to have a hepatoprotective effect, countering liver damage when the subjects were exposed to toxic carbon tetrachloride.12 Trikatu is considered especially beneficial if you have obstructive jaundice, a condition that causes a blockage of bile flow to the intestine, resulting in symptoms of dark yellow urine and yellowish skin and eyes.13




6. Fights Inflammatory Conditions Like Rheumatoid Arthritis And Gout

Autoimmune inflammatory disorders can often be hard to beat. For those with the aches and pains from rheumatoid arthritis, some days can be a real struggle. If you're looking for respite, the anti-inflammatory properties of trikatu may be just what the doctor ordered. Animal studies back up trikatu's claim of being a potential anti-arthritic remedy.14 It may help properly modulate your body's immune response while cutting the characteristic inflammation associated with the disorder.15

Gouty arthritis or gout causes your joints to become swollen, red, and painful due to the excess uric acid buildup in the body that forms sharp crystals in your joints.16 Animal studies show that trikatu was able to stabilize biochemical changes like enzyme levels that go awry in anyone with gout. It also eased inflammation in affected test animals. In addition, the remedy had a pain-relieving or analgesic effect.17




7. Reduces Risk of Atherosclerosis And Hyperlipidemia

When plaque from fat, cholesterol, and other substances builds up in your arteries over time, it can cause them to narrow. This condition known as atherosclerosis is potentially dangerous because it doesn't just reduce how much oxygen or blood your body can supply to your vital organs, it also raises the risk of your developing a blood clot that could cut off flow to the brain and heart.18

Which is where trikatu comes in. The herbal remedy has the ability to reduce levels of both low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol as well as triglycerides and increase your "good" high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol - in effect, helping you maintain a healthy cholesterol ratio. This cuts your risk of a high cholesterol problem or hyperlipidemia as well as atherosclerosis.

Animal studies have backed up this with evidence and later human studies show promise too.19 For instance, in one study, patients with hypercholesteremia or high cholesterol levels who took 3 gm of trikatu churna twice a day after meals along with lukewarm water experienced improvement in their lipid profile in 3 months' time. They also did not experience any adverse side effects.20



8. Improves Sexual And Reproductive Health

Trikatu may help you in the bedroom as it is believed to be a natural aphrodisiac. This warming formulation also strengthens the function of your reproductive organs, energizing them and boosting reproductive health in both men and women.21



9. May Treat Skin Diseases

Trikatu is also traditionally used for treating skin diseases.22 For instance, it is used in many ayurvedic regimens to treat psoriasis or eczema. Ancient ayurvedic texts describe the use of trikatu along with ayurvedic remedy haritaki as well as jaggery and sesame oil for a period of one month to cure skin diseases. Pitta problems like itchiness of the skin can also be improved by having trikatu.



10. May Help Improve Effectiveness Of Other Medicines

Trikatu is also a bioenhancer - a substance that helps make other drugs become more readily available and effective in the body. Such substances are usually given to patients along with their regular medication to help that treatment become more effective. For example, rifampicin, an antibiotic used for treating tuberculosis and leprosy, is increasingly coming up against mutant strains of bacteria resistant to it. However, if combined with trikatu, some of the effectiveness of the drug is restored. This makes the herbal remedy a vital addition to the treatment arsenal for such illnesses in the face of drug-resistant bacteria.

Similarly, if you need to take the anti-seizure medication phenytoin, heart medication/beta blocker propranolol, or respiratory ailment medication theophylline, trikatu could help boost their effectiveness. That said, further and wider human trials are needed to establish this benefit.23 24 So do not discontinue your medication or alter your dosage of any of these drugs. Instead, consult your doctor about how best to combine the benefits of the mainstream and alternative remedies.


Using Trikatu Safely

Trikatu is typically taken in small doses combined with either water, or honey, or milk. For adults taking it on a regular basis, the amount of powder taken should be very small - often less than even a quarter of a teaspoon. Doses are typically under 1 gm though you may sometimes need to take more.25 For children, the dosage may be as little as 125 mg. Pregnant women should avoid the remedy altogether, though nursing mothers may be cleared to take it after consulting their doctor.26

Do check with a trained ayurvedic practitioner on how much you should take and how often. Having very large doses may result in a burning sensation internally or burning sensation while urinating due to the heating properties of the remedy. If this happens to you, take cooling agents like milk to soothe the body immediately, discontinue the medication, and consult your doctor on next steps, modified dosages, or alternative remedies."</string>

    <string name="turmeric_details">"Throughout history, our ancestors have relied on numerous herbs and spices, not only for cooking but for their powerful healing properties. Few have survived the test of time quite like turmeric, arguably the most well-studied dietary supplement in modern natural medicine.

Turmeric root powder originates from the Curcuma longa plant, a species of ginger native to Southeast Asia. The curcuminoids within it have potent anti-inflammatory and antioxidant activity with a wide variety of uses and benefits and very few side effects.

The best turmeric supplements have a combination of curcumin and black pepper (piperine) to enhance absorption and maximize efficacy. But what are the health benefits of turmeric and curcumin pills?



1) Helps Arthritis &amp; Joint Pain

One of the most common uses for turmeric extract is combating the discomfort from joint pain and arthritis. Severe arthritic symptoms include limited range of motion, joint stiffness, excessive swelling, and lack of mobility. These symptoms can get worse over time, causing permanent damage if left untreated.

Research shows that curcumin inhibits many of the mediators of inflammation linked to rheumatoid arthritis, psoriatic arthritis, and osteoarthritis development. Turmeric consistently reduces arthritis symptomology and may serve as an excellent complementary treatment for joint pain.




2) Reduces Chronic Inflammation

Inflammation is the body’s immune system responding to irritants or threats. Inflamed areas often swell up, turn red, or become painful. While this is a healthy and normal bodily reaction, sometimes the immune system goes awry. If inflammation becomes chronic, it can lead to significant health problems.

Many trials have demonstrated curcumin’s anti-inflammatory properties through its inhibition of key inflammatory markers in the body. Turmeric’s antioxidant activity also helps reduce oxidative stress, a process linked to low-grade inflammation.



Back Pain

Often, chronic back pain derives from underlying issues, including sciatica, herniated disks, or spinal problems. While turmeric is not a direct cure for these conditions, it has shown potential in managing upper and lower back pain by targeting inflammation and reducing free radical damage.






3) Aids Weight Loss

Obesity can lead to several different health issues, such as high blood pressure, diabetes, heart disease, stroke, and others. If you’re an otherwise healthy individual, weight loss can be pretty straight forward. However, if you have a pre-existing metabolic disorder, things can be a bit more complicated.

Several trials have shown that curcumin benefits metabolic disorders by helping stabilize metabolism and managing weight. Turmeric increases insulin sensitivity, regulates lipid metabolism, and targets fat by suppressing multiple processes responsible for the growth of adipose tissue.





4) Improves Skin Health

Our skin is the all-important, outermost protective layer of our body. Skin keeps us safe from harmful microbes and regulates our internal body temperature. At times, unwanted skin conditions may arise that require treatment such as chronic acne, eczema, and psoriasis.

Many DIYers use turmeric powder to create face masks, pastes, and other topical solutions to heal the skin. Researchers have confirmed that curcumin reduces oxidative stress associated with inflammatory skin conditions. Turmeric also enhances collagen synthesis and significantly speeds up tissue repair.





5) Natural Blood Thinner

Blood clots occur when blood cells called platelets, move to a damage site to plug the wounded area. This occurrence is a normal bodily function. Without clotting, small papercuts would become catastrophic. At times, certain health conditions arise that require blood thinning to prevent blockages.

Curcumin supplements have shown potential as an anticoagulant (blood thinner) under certain conditions. Turmeric extract impacts several stages of the coagulation process, including thrombosis (local blood clotting), and hemostasis (stopping blood flow). However, more human trials should be done to confirm efficacy.



6) Helps Fight Disease &amp; Chronic Conditions

The potent antioxidant properties may be one of the most significant turmeric benefits. Curcumin has shown an innate ability to boost immune system function and protect against disease by directly inhibiting free radical cell damage and reducing oxidative stress. Turmeric can help with the following:
Cancer

Researchers have performed numerous trials on turmeric’s potential to serve as a complementary treatment in cancer patients. They’ve found that curcumin can selectively target cancer cells and inhibit tumor initiation and growth. Turmeric also helps reduce inflammation and pain from chemotherapy.





Diabetes

If you’re attempting to lower your blood sugar or prevent diabetes, turmeric may be able to help. Several trials have demonstrated curcumin’s potential in patients with type 1 or type 2 diabetes. Curcumin appears to have both an insulin-sensitizing and glucose-lowering effect while improving glycemic regulation.






High Blood Pressure (Hypertension)

Stabilizing blood pressure and preventing hypertension is one of the most common uses of turmeric. It won’t be able to overcome poor lifestyle choices that lead to high blood pressure. However, curcumin has shown an ability to improve vascular endothelial function, a modulator of blood pressure that declines with age.






Alzheimer’s &amp; Dementia

Research shows that an oral turmeric supplement may be one of the best ways to prevent dementia and Alzheimer’s disease. Curcuminoids can help reduce beta-amyloid plaque buildup on the brain and reduce neuroinflammation, two of the key biomarkers linked to Alzheimer’s development.



Regulates Cholesterol

Under certain conditions, clinical trials have concluded that turmeric can help lower triglycerides and cholesterol levels. Current evidence suggests curcumin may be beneficial if you are obese, have metabolic syndrome, diabetes, or another chronic condition affecting your blood lipid profile.





Candida Overgrowth

We know the primary turmeric health benefits include its antibacterial, antiviral, anti-inflammatory, and antioxidant activity. Current evidence suggests curcumin also contains antifungal properties. Multiple tests concluded that turmeric could reduce candida overgrowth and target fungal infections with moderate success.




Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS)

With new research emerging indicating that IBS patients frequently see an increase in the body’s inflammatory response, we now have a new treatment target. Curcumin powder has shown potential in reducing IBS severity and limiting symptoms such as abdominal pain, bloating, and constipation.




Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD)

Ulcerative colitis and Crohn’s disease may develop due to continuing inflammation in the gastrointestinal tract. Curcumin has shown significant potential in treating IBD by inhibiting the upregulation of pro-inflammatory markers linked to chronic and relapsing GI tract problems.



Fibromyalgia &amp; Chronic Fatigue Syndrome

At this time, there is no identified cure for fibromyalgia and chronic fatigue syndrome, but there are ample ways to control symptoms and flare-ups. Researchers have evidence to suggest that turmeric supplements may help reduce widespread musculoskeletal pain by inhibiting inflammatory pathways and reducing oxidative stress.



Parkinson’s Disease

Parkinson’s is a neurodegenerative condition in elderly populations characterized by motor symptoms, including tremors, muscle rigidity, and postural instability. Curcumin shows significant neuroprotective benefits, helping reduce neurotoxicity and oxidative stress linked to disease progression.






7) Enhances Brain Function

Improving overall mental health and cognitive function is one of the most popular turmeric uses. Research shows curcumin enhances DHA synthesis which is critical for brain health. Antioxidants can also improve cognition and increase neuroplasticity, the brain’s capacity to create new synaptic connections.






Reduces Anxiety &amp; Depression

Several clinical trials have shown that turmeric extract can influence neurotransmitter balance in the brain. Curcumin appears to have an antidepressant and anxiolytic effect through its ability to modulate levels of serotonin and dopamine. Thus, it may be a good complementary treatment for depression.






8) Improves Allergies &amp; Asthma

An allergy transpires when the immune system mistakenly identifies a foreign substance as harmful to the body and overreacts to it. During an allergic reaction, we produce antibodies that respond to these allergens, ultimately leading to an unwanted collection of symptoms (coughing, sneezing, itching, etc.).

The anti-inflammatory activity of turmeric powder can help fight off many allergy-related symptoms and decrease the likelihood of asthma attacks. Current research suggests a curcumin supplement can reduce signs of sneezing, nasal congestion, and runny nose linked to restricted nasal airflow and hay fever.







9) Aids in Liver Detoxification

A liver detox, also known as a cleanse, involves the removal of toxins from the blood and the metabolizing of nutrients to ensure our body gets what it needs. Think of the liver as the body’s central filtration system. A healthy liver is paramount to optimal physical and mental health.

Several trials have demonstrated curcumin’s ability to limit the damage done to the liver from harmful substances by interrupting inflammatory pathways. Turmeric also stimulates bile production and release from the gallbladder, helping eliminate unwanted waste from the body.





10) Helps Headaches &amp; Migraines

Headaches and migraines are tremendously difficult to handle. The immense pain and discomfort can arise from many factors including stress, fatigue, insufficient sleep, inflammation, poor posture, neck tension, and several other causes.

The benefits of curcumin that have shown the most potential in treating headaches and migraines are its anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties. The exact mechanisms are unknown, but it appears that turmeric can reduce pain linked to inflammation, and directly inhibit oxidative stress in the body.
Final Thoughts on Health Benefits of Turmeric Curcumin

If you’re wondering “what is turmeric good for,” the answer is almost everything. It’s important to note; turmeric supplements are not a cure for diseases or chronic conditions. But, the unique medicinal properties of curcumin have shown significant health benefits and uses in modern natural medicine.


In nearly every study, turmeric root extract has demonstrated that it’s both effective, well-tolerated at higher dosages, and void of adverse side effects. If you’re considering adding turmeric pills to your regimen, always consult with a doctor or primary care physician, first. It’s vital to make sure that any dietary supplement you’re taking does not conflict with any pre-existing medications."</string>

    <string name="bitter_melon_details">"Bitter melon, or Goya, is commonly used for beneficial health reasons. Bitter melon is also referred to as bitter gourd, Karela, or Balsam Pear. The melon has an extremely bitter taste, but it is a helpful food. Bitter melon is commonly added to stir-fry, or may be enjoyed stuffed. It may also be added to the diet as a supplement. In order to receive the full health benefits, find and cook the melon regularly.

Here’s some sweet information you need to know about this bitter vegetable:



1. Type II Diabetes

Some studies have shown that bitter melon lowers blood sugar through increased metabolism of glucose. Drink one cup daily. Try this recipe to receive the full benefit of the fruit. As with any changes to your diet, be sure you consult you physician. Stop use if you’re experiencing abdominal pain, diarrhea, or fever. Monitor blood sugar regularly and adjust medications as necessary, with the assistance of your doctor.



2. Kidney Stones

A kidney stone is an extremely painful medical condition. Bitter melon can be helpful in ridding the body of kidney stones through naturally breaking them down. Bitter melon reduces high acid that help produce painful kidney stones. Infuse bitter melon powder with water to create a healthful tea. This tea has a nutty flavor and, surprisingly, does not require sweetening.



3. Lower Cholesterol

Help lower dangerous cholesterol levels with bitter melon. Reducing cholesterol significantly reduces heart attack, heart disease, and stroke. The added benefit is that bitter melon is completely natural in working with the body to prevent these health risks. High cholesterol can only be diagnosed with a blood test. Try Bitter Melon Delight to reap the reward of this surprising health benefit.



4. Pancreatic Cancer

One of the most surprising health benefits of bitter melon is its anti-cancer properties. Bitter melon has been shown to disrupt the production of glucose, potentially inhibiting the growth of pancreatic cancer cells. Bitter melon may also starve other cancerous cells in the liver, colon, breast, or prostate.



5. Skin Benefits

Foods or drink taken from this melon benefit the skin. Taken regularly, bitter melon is said to have a “glowing” effect on the skin and is helpful in treating acne, psoriasis, and eczema. Experience natural and soothing relief with bitter melon. Try bitter melon soup for relief of any of these skin conditions or for more beautiful skin. An added benefit is that bitter melon is a blood-purifying agent.




6. Weight Loss

As is common with most plants, bitter melon is extremely low in calories and very filling. Lose, or maintain a healthy weight, with bitter melon. Prepare stuffed bitter melon to enjoy this benefit.The same properties that aid against Type II Diabetes also assist in health weigh loss and maintenance. The melon is very high in nutrients, which is another reason it’s so beneficial in weight loss.



7. Liver Tonic

There are several benefits of regularly consuming a liver tonic. A tonic aids in digestion, improves gallbladder function, and lowers fluid retention. Cirrhosis of the liver, hepatitis, and constipation may be relieved with a bitter melon liver tonic. Drink a bitter melon juice at least once a day to enjoy the benefits. A liver tonic is also aids in weight loss, and may relieve the symptoms of irritable bowel system.



8. Carbohydrate Digestion

This is a very important benefit for those who have Type II Diabetes. Carbohydrates turn to sugar, and bitter melon metabolizes the sugars. Faster metabolism of carbohydrates means that less fat is stored in the body which leads to weight loss, and healthy weight maintenance. Proper carbohydrate digestion also aids in muscle growth and development. A Bitter Melon Stir-Fry is just the ticket for the many benefits of bitter melon.



9. Vitamin-K Source

Vitamin-K contributes to bone health, blood-clotting, and is an anti-inflammatory. Those suffering from arthritis can experience lower pain and inflammation in the joints through increasing Vitamin-K. No-Fry Karela Crispies are a delicious way to add Vitamin-K to your diet. The addition of bitter melon satisfies your body’s daily nutritional need for Vitamin-K. Also, the addition of bitter melon is a great source for dietary fiber.


10. Increased Immunity

 A healthy immune system is vital for fending off potential infections and diseases. Add this delicious and easily prepared Bitter Melon Stir-Fry for this added health benefit. Stop or prevent a cold instantly in its tracks while benefiting the digestive system. Prevent or curb food allergies, and get rid of yeast infections, naturally. An added bonus of bitter melon is relief of acid reflux and indigestion.
        "</string>
    <string name="artichoke">"10 Artichoke Health Benefits You Def Want To Get In On"</string>
    <string name="artichoke_details">"Artichokes are regal-looking veggies that pop up a frequently in salads as they do on cheesy take-out pizza…so how healthy can they be? In short: Pretty darn healthy. "Artichokes have calcium, vitamin C, vitamin A, and iron," says Kim Kirchherr, R.D..

While many R.D.s recommend eating produce raw to retain as many vitamins and minerals as possible, you can make an exception with artichokes, says Nadja Pinnavaia, Ph.D. and founder of Euphebe Healthcare. Because, as she points out, raw artichokes aren't exactly palatable.

Whether you choose to steam or boil them, artichokes are a great appetizer, side dish, or snack that pack all kinds of good-for-you perks.



1. They're full of nutrients.

As Kirchherr mentions above, these little veggies are chock-full of important nutrients, like vitamin C, vitamin A, and iron, "as well as potassium and antioxidants," she says.

Here's the full nutrition breakdown of one medium artichoke:

    64 calories
    .4g fat
    7g fiber
    14.3g carbs
    3.5g protein
    1g sugar



2. They contain a ton of protein.

In addition to its wide nutrition profile,"artichokes offer more protein than many other vegetables at 3.5 grams per serving," says Kris Sollid, R.D., senior director of nutrition communications at the International Food Information Council Foundation. Bonus: Research from the Journal of the American College of Cardiology found that those who consume a higher ratio of plant-based protein to animal-derived protein have a reduced risk of coronary heart disease.



3. They’re high in fiber.

It’s no secret that fiber helps move your digestion along and keeps you feeling full, but it also offers more long-term benefits like a lower risk of heart disease. According to Sollid, a half cup of artichokes contains about seven grams of fiber, or more than a quarter of the amount recommended for women and nearly a fifth of the amount recommended for men. "Americans only eat about half the amount of fiber that\'s recommended per day," he says, so a serving of artichoke is certainly a step in the right direction.



4. They can strengthen your gut.

Artichokes are full of inulin, according to Sollid, which is a "unique form of fiber known to help prevent gastrointestinal issues like constipation, enhance the absorption of minerals like calcium, and bolster your immune system."

According to a study from the British Journal of Nutrition, inulin also works as a prebiotic, which helps your body maintain a healthy gut.



5. They may boost your immune system.

Orange juice isn’t the only thing that’ll help keep you from contracting your co-worker’s cold. In fact, the Journal of Agriculture and Food Chemistry ranked artichokes high up on the list of immune-boosting, antioxidant-rich foods.



6. They’re high in polyphenols.

Speaking of a healthy immune system, Pinnavaia says that artichokes are naturally high in polyphenols, which can repair damaged cells that impair your immune function.
Polyphenols are a group of phytochemicals found largely in plant foods that foods that contribute to their color, says Kirchherr. And research from the Journal of Cell Physiology found that they help protect against disease.




7. They can help treat allergies.

According to Pinnavaia, a diet rich in vegetables, like artichokes, has the potential to suppress inflammation.

Sollid says artichokes are an excellent source of folate, which is a B vitamin that researchers have found to be potentially beneficial in reducing inflammation that causes allergies and asthma. It's also important during pregnancy.



8. They can help lower body fat.

While no food item can single-handedly make you drop pounds, a recent study from Pharmacological Research found that artichokes are certainly helpful in maintaining a healthy bodyweight. "An artichoke has about 25 calories, so it easily fits into a menu that supports healthy weight management," says Kircherr.



9. They may help reduce the risk of cancer.

In that same vein, reducing inflammation also helps reduce the potential for cancer cell growth, according to Pinnavaia. Artichokes have been shown to help fight a number of specific cancers, too: Their flavonoid content helps kill pancreatic cancer cells, according to a study from Molecular Nutrition and Food Research. And since artichokes are among the highest sources of the flavonoid apigenin (a type of plant nutrient), they can help fight breast cancer, too, according to the Journal of Clinical Biochemistry and Nutrition.




10. They’re a whole food.

A study from the journal Nutrition and Diabetes found that those who adhere to a whole food plant-based diet experience a reduction in cholesterol and body mass index. Sollid makes a case for making whole artichokes part of that plan: "There are unquestioned health benefits to eating a diet that is high in vegetables like artichokes," he says. "Seeking nutrients from whole foods is always the best approach."

In case you're curious, here's the healthiest way to prep an artichoke:

    Grab a steamer pot, and add a small amount of water with a squeeze of lemon juice.
    Add one tablespoon of salt and bring to a boil.
    Trim the spiky leaves, then place the artichokes stem-side up in the steamer basket after having trimmed their spiky leaves.
    Cover pot, steam for 25 to 30 minutes, until heart is tender when pierced with a knife and inner leaves pull out easily.

And voila! You've got yourself a healthy snack, appetizer, or side dish. Just try to go light on the butter or mayo dip, and opt for a healthier dip alternative like Greek yogurt with herbs.
        "</string>
    <string name="ashwagandha_details">"
Ashwagandha, also known as 'Withania Somnifera', was originally used in traditional Indian Ayurvedic medicine. This herb is becoming increasingly popular in the west and is most well known for its ability to reduce stress and promote a calmer and happier sense of being. A growing body of evidence is being collated around this powerful herb with an impressive variety of health benefits.

Ashwagandha is an adaptogenic meaning it can adapt to your body’s needs by balancing out levels, such as hormones and immune cells, to create stability in the body and support our immune system. Here are 5 key health benefits of this powerful adaptogenic:




1. Supports adrenal glands to reduce stress and anxiety

Ashwagandha has been shown to support the adrenals via normalising cortisol levels. This reduces the negative effects of high (or low levels) of this hormone. This is highly significant as ongoing stress can be detrimental to our health. Adrenal function is closely linked to thyroid function, therefore as Ashwagandha supports the adrenal glands, it has an indirect effect on improving thyroid function as well. Initial studies demonstrate ashwagandha’s ability to positively impact thyroid function by stimulating thyroid hormone activity. Our Food-Grown® KSM-66 Ashwagandha Plus provides 500mg of organic ashwagandha root with Food-Grown® Magnesium to support the body's resilience to physiological and psychological demand.




2. Increases energy, stamina and endurance

Ashwagandha has been shown to significantly impact athletic performance by improving heart and lung capacity while increasing energy levels. Not only is this useful for the purposes of exercise, it is also helpful for people who struggle with their energy levels or those with fatigue-related conditions.



3. Stabilises blood sugar

Ashwagandha has been shown to stabilise blood sugar levels, reducing blood sugar when it's too high or increasing it if too low. This is an example of the herb’s adaptogenic effect. Considering the evidence of the impact on blood sugar levels in diseases such as depression and dementia, this herb can have a profound impact on health.



4. Combats neurodegenerative diseases

The active ingredients in ashwagandha, called withanamides, have shown protective effects against B-amyloid-induced plaques in Alzheimer’s Disease. This is thought to be due to the natural antioxidants found in ashwagandha that scavenge free radicals to prevent cell damage. Studies also show promising results of ashwagandha’s protective effects against Parkinson’s Disease.



5. Immune boosting and anti-inflammatory


It has also demonstrated excellent immune-boosting effects on our immune system. It has been shown to encourage anti-inflammatory and disease-fighting immune cells that help to ward off illness. As Ashwagandha has potent anti-inflammatory properties it is very useful in painful conditions such as arthritis. As the herb is rich in iron it also contributes to red blood cell count.
        "</string>
    <string name="gotucola_detaisl">"
Gotu kola is a perennial herb native to Asia. People have used gotu kola in traditional medicine for many years, due to its potential health properties.

Some people believe that gotu kola may help heal wounds, improve cognition, and lower blood pressure.

Despite the herb’s long history of use, very few clinical studies have found that gotu kola supplements have health benefits. People who take these supplements likely rely on anecdotal evidence.

In this article, we explore whether there are research-supported benefits of gotu kola, as well as possible adverse effects.



What is it?

Gotu kola may help treat varicose veins.

Gotu kola’s scientific name is Centella asiatica. The plant is native to tropical and subtropical parts of Asia.

According to an older review of studies, gotu kola contains compounds such as triterpenoid saponins. Researchers believe that these may be largely responsible for the plant’s purported health benefits.

Some traditional uses of gotu kola include:

    healing wounds
    relieving diarrhea
    boosting energy levels
    reducing anxiety
    enhancing sexual potency
    treating venereal diseases
    treating skin diseases
    treating menstrual disorders
    slowing leprosy progression
    prolonging life

There is limited clinical evidence, however, to support many of these uses.

In fact, the authors of a 2018 review of studies indicated that more research is necessary before the medical community can approve the widespread use of gotu kola. Their recommendations included:

    fully understanding the active ingredients
    fully understanding how gotu kola may affect medications
    determining how to best extract and stabilize the active compounds
    determining how likely the compounds are to reach the right areas of the body



Researchers have investigated the following uses of gotu kola:



Treating varicose veins

According to the Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, several studies claim that gotu kola can help treat varicose veins and venous insufficiency.

However, many of these studies date back to the early 2000s or earlier — more up-to-date research is necessary.

For example, an older study, from 2001, found that participants who received 60 milligrams of triterpenic fraction of gotu kola twice daily for 8 weeks experienced improvements in the health of their veins.

The participants all had conditions with significant vein involvement, such as severe venous hypertension and ankle swelling.

Another study from the same year, and from some of the same researchers, produced similar results.

The second study found that gotu kola extracts helped with diabetic microangiopathy by improving the function of the veins. This health issue affects people with diabetes and involves having unusually small blood vessels in various areas of the body.




Wound and burn healing

According to a 2010 review of studies, some research supports the use of gotu kola to help wounds and burns heal.

The authors reported that many studies had found that gotu kola sped up wound healing.

However, most of these studies involved animals or artificial wounds created in labs. This means that the herb may not have the same effects in humans.

The authors also noted that a lack of medical supervision and knowledge about how gotu kola might react with medications made the herb potentially dangerous to use.

The Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center also highlight the lack of trials in humans and call for further testing before the effectiveness of gotu kola as a wound treatment can be confirmed.



Improving cognitive function

According to one review of studies, gotu kola may help support the functioning of the brain and nervous system, improve memory, and protect against aging.

However, more recent studies do not support some of these claims. A 2017 study found that gotu kola may improve alertness and reduce anger but did not substantiate the other findings.

Meanwhile, in a 2016 study, researchers looked at people who had experienced cognitive impairment following a stroke.

They found that few, if any, improvements were associated with using gotu kola, compared with folic acid. However, the authors noted that some participants experienced some improvement in long-term memory after taking the herbal extract."</string>

    <string name="chocolate_details">"For an antioxidant boost, break off a square of dark chocolate.

If you’ve dreamt of eating chocolate every day, now you have an excuse — or eight.

Scientific studies have shown that dark chocolate — sorry, milk and white chocolate don’t count — is rich in antioxidants and packed with nutrients, making this bittersweet treat a superfood favorite.

Dark chocolate contains phytonutrients called flavonoids, which are plant chemicals that act as antioxidants and may play a role in cancer prevention, heart health, and weight loss, noted an article published in December 2016 in the Journal of Nutritional Science. The cacao plant that chocolate is derived from also contains a compound called theobromine, which Toby Amidor, RD, a cookbook author and nutrition expert for the Food Network, says can help reduce inflammation and potentially lower blood pressure.

“Cacao is packed with numerous antioxidants — actually more than green tea or red wine,” she says. “The darker you go, the more antioxidants you’ll get, but there needs to be a balance between eating palatable dark chocolate and getting the health benefits.”

Your best bet is choosing a bar with 70 percent cacao or higher, according to the Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health; bars with lower percentages of cacao have more added sugar and unhealthy fats. Even though quality dark chocolate is a better choice than milk chocolate, it is still chocolate, meaning it’s high in calories and saturated fat. To avoid weight gain, Amidor recommends eating no more than 1 ounce of dark chocolate per day. Now, a look at what this treat offers.



1.Dark Chocolate May Help Prevent Heart Disease and Lower the Risk of Stroke

One of the biggest benefits that researchers tout is the role dark chocolate may play in improving heart health. A meta-analysis of eight studies on the link between chocolate consumption and cardiovascular disease, published in July 2015 in the journal Heart, found that people who ate more chocolate per day had a lower risk of both heart disease and stroke.

A number of observational studies have also shown indulging in dark chocolate on a regular basis may reduce the risk of heart disease. For example, one earlier study published in the journal Clinical Nutrition found that people who ate dark chocolate more than five times a week reduced their risk of heart disease by 57 percent.

Researchers hypothesize it’s the flavonoids in dark chocolate that maintain heart health, per a study published in The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition. These chemicals help produce nitric oxide, which causes blood vessels to relax and blood pressure to lower, noted a review published in March 2017 in the American Journal of Physiology: Cell Physiology.

Because many of these studies are observational, the results could be skewed by people underreporting their chocolate intake. The studies are also limited in that they can’t directly establish cause and effect. More study is needed to determine the exact amount and types of flavonoid-rich chocolate that would help lessen stroke risk.




2.The Treat May Improve Cognition, Prevent Memory Loss, and Boost Your Mood

No, it’s not your imagination — studies show consuming high concentrations of dark chocolate may benefit your brain. Joy DuBost, PhD, RD, a nutrition spokesperson and owner of Dubost Food &amp; Nutrition Solutions, says research has shown chocolate stimulates neural activity in areas of the brain associated with pleasure and reward, which in turn decreases stress and improves your mood.

Out of eight studies on chocolate and mood, five showed improvements in mood, and three showed “clear evidence of cognitive enhancement,” according to a systematic review published in the journal Nutrition Reviews. Further research presented at the 2018 Experimental Biology meeting found that eating 48 grams (g) of organic chocolate with 70 percent cacao increased neuroplasticity in the brain, which could have positive effects on memory, cognition, and mood.

Improvements in brain health may be due to the high levels of flavonoids in dark chocolate, which research, like a study published in April 2018 in The FASEB Journal, has found to have accumulated in regions of the brain responsible for learning and memory.

While some research, including a study published in May 2017 in the journal Frontiers in Nutrition, has indicated there may be a link between dark chocolate and the brain, studies with larger sample sizes need to be conducted, and further research is needed to investigate the mechanisms involved. And before you run out and stock up on chocolate bars, keep in mind most studies experimented with much higher quantities of chocolate than the recommended daily dose (1.5 ounces maximum).




3.Dark Chocolate Could Improve Blood Sugar Levels, and Reduce the Risk of Developing Diabetes

Eating chocolate every day doesn’t sound like the best way to prevent diabetes, but studies have shown healthy amounts of dark chocolate rich in cacao could actually improve how the body metabolizes glucose. Insulin resistance causes high blood glucose (sugar) and is the hallmark of type 2 diabetes, per an article published in March 2019 by StatPearls.

In a study published in October 2017 the Journal of Community and Hospital Internal Medicine Perspectives, the flavonoids in dark chocolate were found to reduce oxidative stress, which scientists think is the primary cause of insulin resistance. By improving your body’s sensitivity to insulin, resistance is reduced, and in turn the risk of diseases like diabetes decreases.

Another study, this one published in January 2017 in the journal Appetite, showed that participants who rarely consumed chocolate had almost twice the risk of developing diabetes five years down the road, compared with participants who indulged in dark chocolate at least once per week.

While researchers agree dark chocolate possesses many health benefits, further study is needed to determine if there is a cause-and-effect relationship between chocolate consumption and diabetes risk.



4.Chocolate Is Good for Your Gut and May Help With Weight Loss

Eating chocolate every day probably seems like the last way to lose weight, but research suggests dark chocolate may play a role in controlling appetite, which in turn could help with weight loss. Neuroscientist Will Clower, PhD, wrote a whole book on the subject called Eat Chocolate, Lose Weight, which describes how eating a bit of dark chocolate before or after meals triggers hormones that signal to the brain you’re full. Of course, eating more than the recommended amount per day can counteract any potential weight loss.

Studies cited in an article published in the journal Frontiers in Pharmacology furthermore noted that during digestion, chocolate behaves like a prebiotic (not to be confused with probiotic), a type of fiber that encourages the growth of beneficial bacteria in the gut. The more “good” microbes are in your system, the better your body is able to absorb nutrients as well as support a healthy metabolism, according to the Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health.




5.It Fights Free Radicals and May Play a Role in Cancer Prevention
Evidence that dark chocolate possesses properties that could help protect people from certain types of cancer is limited but growing. Antioxidants protect our cells from damage caused by free radicals, which are unstable oxygen molecules thought to be responsible for aging and disease, per an article published in January 2015 in the Indian Journal of Clinical Biochemistry.

“When you have too many free radicals in your body, they start to attack your cells, and that can lead, over time, to low-grade inflammation and to some diseases — cancer, heart disease, and Alzheimer’s,” Dr. DuBost says.

Some studies, such as one published in the Journal of the American Society of Hypertension, have shown that people who eat many flavonoids or antioxidant-rich chocolate develop fewer cancers than those who don’t consume them. Of the many flavonoids in chocolate, two in particular, epicatechin and quercetin, are believed to be responsible for the cancer-fighting properties.

Still, most studies are limited in using only animals or cell cultures, and the amount of chocolate needed to potentially yield preventative action against cancers is much higher than the daily recommended dose for humans, noted a review published in The Netherlands Journal of Medicine.




6.It's Good for Your Skin (in More Ways Than One)

The Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health lists vitamins and minerals dark chocolate is packed full of — like copper, iron, and magnesium, to name a few — that are also beneficial to your skin. Manganese, for example, supports the production of collagen, a protein that helps keep skin looking young and healthy. Other minerals, like calcium, help repair and renew skin, which is pretty important because, according to the American Academy of Dermatology, our bodies can shed up to 40,000 skin cells each day! Several earlier studies have also found the high levels of antioxidants in dark chocolate may protect skin from the powerful ultraviolet (UV) rays emitted by the sun.

Other research, like a study published in June 2014 in Nutrition Journal, failed to show any significant protective effects of antioxidant-rich chocolate against UV rays, but did show improvements in the elasticity of skin exposed to the sun, although the exact mechanism of this isn’t known.



7.Dark Chocolate May Send Good Cholesterol up, Bad Cholesterol Down

Dark chocolate is also touted as a cholesterol-lowering food. A handful of almonds, dark chocolate, and unsweetened cocoa showed a significant drop in low-density lipoproteins (LDL), also known as “bad” cholesterol, which in high amounts can clog arteries, in a study published in November 2017 in the Journal of the American Heart Association.

DuBost says the cocoa butter in dark chocolate may also play a part in raising high-density lipoproteins (HDL), or “good” cholesterol. Cocoa butter contains oleic acid, which is a monounsaturated fat — the same fat you find in heart-healthy olive oil, notes the U.S. Library of Medicine. However, unlike olive oil, cocoa butter is also high in saturated fat (per the U.S. Department of Agriculture), which in excess can be harmful to the heart, further emphasizing the need for portion control.

Not to mention, many of the studies on chocolate and good cholesterol are short term, so it’s premature to say that chocolate is a cholesterol cure-all, DuBost adds.





8.Dark Chocolate Is Nutritious — and Delicious!

On top of all the other potential benefits, one thing is for sure: Dark chocolate contains a ton of nutrients. Of course, the darker the chocolate the better, but any 70 percent dark chocolate or higher contains antioxidants, fiber, potassium, calcium, copper, and magnesium, according to a study published in the journal Antioxidants &amp; Redox Signaling.

It also contains a good chunk of calories and fat, so be mindful of your daily intake. Each brand of chocolate is also processed differently; Amidor says going organic is always best because it’s grown without the use of chemical fertilizers and pesticides (look for Rainforest Alliance Certified products), and recommends always checking the ingredient list to make sure you’re consuming chocolate with fewer and more natural ingredients.

        "</string>
    <string name="nutmeg_details">"India is the land of spices. Walk into the kitchen of a typical Indian household, and you will find a string of containers that are filled with different types of spice, neatly arranged. One such spice that you will find in one of those many containers is nutmeg. Valued for its sweet aroma, this spice is actually the seed of an evergreen tree that is a native of Indonesia, known as myristica fragrans. A lot of Indian cuisines use nutmeg for its aromatic value and unique flavour. But nutmeg is more than just a spice that enhances the taste and smell of food. It has an abundance of nutritional value too.


Nutritional Value of Nutmeg

Here is the nutritional value of 100 grams of ground nutmeg.
    Nutrient                   Value
    Calories 	---------------525
    Total Fat 	---------------36 g
    Carbohydrates -------------49 g
    Protein 	---------------6 g
    Sodium 	-------------------16 mg
    Potassium 	---------------350 mg
    Calcium 	---------------184 mg
    Iron 	-------------------3 mg
    Magnesium 	---------------183 mg
    Calcium 	---------------0.18
    Vitamin C 	---------------3 mg
    Vitamin A 	---------------30 mcg
    Vitamin B6 	---------------0.2 mg
    Niacin 	-------------------1.3mg


1. Helps Improve Digestion

Nutmeg is known to have medicinal properties that can treat stomach ulcers and help in digestion. A lot of people add this spice to food, as it helps with easy digestion. Sometimes, even Indian desserts are laced with a little nutmeg for the same reason.



2. Helps Treat Insomnia

Nutmeg seems to have properties to treat insomnia as well. A little nutmeg, in a glass of warm milk, has proven to induce sleepiness in many people. A lot of mothers give their children warm milk with a little bit of nutmeg powder mixed in it. This is an age-old tradition that has been passed on for generations because it is, in fact, highly effective. In fact, nutmeg for inducing sleep is an organic and healthy way of treating insomnia.




3. Helps Relieve Pain

Nutmeg has anti-inflammatory properties that can help ease pain and discomfort. This spice has chemicals like myristicin, elemicin, safrole, and eugenol that makes it useful for treating pain. These chemicals are found in the oil of nutmeg. The benefits of nutmeg oil include treating swelling, inflammation, joint pain, muscle spasms, pains, and sores.


4. Helps in Brain Activity

Nutmeg works as an aphrodisiac, which means it can stimulate the nerve cells in the brain. The chemicals in this spice can help release feel-good hormones in the body, which in turn has a calming effect on you. Since it lifts your mood and works as a tonic, nutmeg is a great option to help treat stress.



5. Great for Your Skin

If you are on the lookout for a natural product that can do wonders for your skin, then nutmeg is your answer. There are many benefits of nutmeg for face and skin. Its many antimicrobial and anti-inflammatory properties can help keep the skin healthy, supple, and unclog pores and blackheads. Nutmeg works as a great face scrub. The best way to use this spice for your skin is by mixing it in powdered form with honey and gently scrubbing your skin.



6. Helps Treat Bad Breath

Bad breath is an overload toxin in your body. Nutmeg is known to have antibacterial and antimicrobial properties, and this can help clean your system. One of the essential oils that are found in nutmeg is eugenol, which can help relieve a toothache as well. Macelignan, a chemical found in nutmeg, can help prevent cavities.




7. Helps Regulate Blood Pressure and Circulation

Nutmeg is rich in minerals like calcium, potassium, manganese, and iron, all of which help in regulating blood pressure and enhance the circulation of blood. These minerals have the effect of reducing stress, and further, relax the blood vessels and aid in the regulation of blood pressure.



8. Helps Protect the Liver

Nutmeg is rich in myrislignan, which can help treat liver disorders and injuries. Research suggests that the extracts found in nutmeg can help treat hepatitis inflammations. Nutmeg, as mentioned before, has anti-inflammatory properties as well, and can help treat an inflamed liver. It can also help remove toxins for the body, particularly the liver.




9. Has Antidepressant Properties

Nutmeg has a calming effect on the body, which makes it a great antidepressant. A lot of Ayurvedic-based medicines use this spice as a part of the medication in treating depression and anxiety.


10. Has Anti-Cancer Properties

Nutmeg has chemopreventive properties that can help prevent cancer. The chemical myristicin present in nutmeg can help fight the growth of cancer cells and the metastasis of leukaemia.



11. Helps Lower Cholesterol Levels

Consuming nutmeg in appropriate quantities has shown to lower cholesterol levels as well. This spice has the property of lowering hypolipidemic effects that help trigger a rise in cholesterol levels.



12. Helps Provide Relief from Diarrhoea

While we’ve earlier mentioned that nutmeg helps with digestion, this spice can help treat and provide relief from diarrhoea as well. Nutmeg has chemicals with carminative properties. The best way to consume nutmeg for treating diarrhoea is by consuming it with cold water.




13. Nutmeg for Hair Growth

Nutmeg is a great organic product for hair growth as well. The antimicrobial properties that it possesses can help keep the scalp clean and prevent dandruff. There are many over-the-counter shampoos that have nutmeg as the base ingredient, and you can purchase this, or you can make your own hair remedy with nutmeg powder, coconut oil, and honey.



14. Nutmeg for Weight Loss

Nutmeg helps in aiding weight loss as well. It can help the body eliminate toxins, and the digestive properties that it has can help in increasing metabolism, thereby helping with weight loss.
Are There Any Side Effects of Nutmeg?

While nutmeg has several nutritional benefits, too much of this spice can have an adverse effect on your body. Here are a few side effects that come with excessive consumption of nutmeg –


1. Gastrointestinal Reactions

While nutmeg is good for digestion and treating diarrhoea, excessive consumption of this spice can, in fact, further trigger gastrointestinal reactions like diarrhoea, bloating, and even constipation.



2. Can Have a Hallucinogenic Effect

The chemical myristicin that is found in nutmeg has a calming and relaxing effect on the brain’s nerve cells, but consuming too much of this drug has shown to have a hallucinogenic effect as well.



3. Palpitation

Consumption of this spice can cause an upsurge in the rate of your heartbeat. Go for immediate medical attention if you experience heart palpitations.



4. Excessive Consumption Can Adversely Affect Pregnancy

Nutmeg in large quantities can have an adverse effect on pregnant women and the fetus. The hallucinogenic effect it has may be dangerous to the fetus. It also inhibits the production of prostaglandin, which is important in the process of childbirth. Large doses of nutmeg can cause miscarriages in women.



FAQs

Some questions regarding the use and consumption of nutmeg include:


1. How Much Amount of Nutmeg Intake is Safe?

Nutmeg is a great spice with several nutritional benefits but consuming too much of it, even as less as a spoon, can cause discomfort, and larger doses can even cause death. Also, consuming nutmeg on a daily basis is not advised.


2. How to Make Nutmeg Tea?

Nutmeg, as mentioned before, is known for its aromatic value and unique flavour. This makes it a great ingredient for tea. Making nutmeg tea is extremely easy. You need to boil water. To this, you need to add a pinch of nutmeg powder, ginger shreds or powder, sugar, and your usual amount of tea leaves. This has to be again boiled for a few minutes. You can strain the decoction and consume it. You can also add milk to if you like.


3. Is Nutmeg Safe during Pregnancy?

Nutmeg is not the ideal choice for women who are pregnant. Taking any risk during pregnancy can prove to be fatal, so it is advised that you stay away from this spice during your pregnancy.


4. Does Nutmeg Induce Sleep in Infants?

Yes, nutmeg has chemicals that can have a calming and relaxing effect on infants. You can mix nutmeg powder in some warm milk for your little one, just before bedtime. However, make sure you do not give your child too much of this as excessive consumption of nutmeg can be dangerous for health.

Nutmeg is a great spice that has several nutritional benefits. However, it has to be consumed in the right way, in appropriate doses. Make sure you consult a doctor in case you or someone you know has a negative, adverse reaction to this spice after its consumption.
        "</string>
    <string name="ginseng_details">"Adaptogens have recently become the buzziest thing in mainstream wellness, but in Chinese and Ayurvedic cultures, their health benefits have been touted for centuries. Take ginseng. It’s long been used in Eastern medicine, but Western science has only recently started looking into its benefits by comparison.


As more people around the world start working with the plant, it’s important to understand both how it can boost your health, as well as its side effects, says Dana Nahai, RDN. First of all, when speaking about ginseng, Nahai notes that we’re talking about a specific Panax variety, which is native to China, Korea, and North America. “It’s bitter on the palate, and the pharmacological effect is far more potent when used as a tea, tincture, or powder than when infused, fried, or eaten raw,” she says.

And when you’re looking for the herb, quality and bioavailability count for everything,” she explains, adding that you should do your research on the herb or supplement before you buy it. The registered dietitian nutritionist advises buying the whole root intact.

Ginseng refers to eleven different varieties of a short, slow-growing plant with fleshy roots. Ginseng is believed to restore and enhance wellbeing. It is one of the most popular herbal remedies.

The herbs consist of a light-colored, forked-shaped root, a relatively long stalk, and green leaves with an oval shape.

Both American ginseng (Panax quinquefolius, L.) and Asian ginseng (P. Ginseng) are believed to boost energy, lower blood sugar and cholesterol levels, reduce stress, promote relaxation, treat diabetes, and manage sexual dysfunction in men.


Read all about ginseng’s supercharged benefits below.

Ginseng has traditionally been taken to aid a range of medical conditions.

More research is needed to confirm its benefit as a supplement. However, it is claimed that ginsenosides, chemical components found in ginseng, are responsible for the clinical effect of the herb.

Western scientists and health professionals often question the medicinal properties of ginseng. There is no conclusive evidence that determines its true effectiveness.

Ginseng products can vary in their quality and medicinal properties. Checking the ingredients of ginseng products before purchase is strongly recommended. Some products have been found to contain a small or negligible amount of ginseng, and some contain other substances.

Researchers suggest that the following health benefits are linked to ginseng:



1.Increased energy

Ginseng may help stimulate physical and mental activity in people who feel weak and tired. One study revealed that ginseng showed good results in helping cancer patients with fatigue.

However, the energy-boosting effects of ginseng were only seen in people currently undergoing treatment. Ginseng did not show statistically significant improvements in people who had already finished cancer treatment.



2.Sharper cognitive function
Ginseng may improve thinking processes and cognition. Research published in The Cochrane Library examined the accuracy of this claim.

The study says that ginseng seems to demonstrate benefits for cognition, behavior, and quality of life. However, the authors of the review cautioned that despite some positive findings, studies included in the systematic review did not make a convincing case for the effectiveness of ginseng as a cognitive booster.

Richard Brown, M.D., an associate professor of clinical psychiatry at Columbia University, said about the study:

    “It was a very careful review. But as with many Chinese herbs and treatments, while ginseng has been used by millions of people, there aren’t a lot of rigorous modern studies.”

Another study, published in Journal of Dairy Science, explored whether it would be possible to incorporate American ginseng into foods. The researchers developed ginseng-fortified milk with sufficient levels of ginseng to improve cognitive function.

However, it is not possible at this stage to know whether the inclusion of ginseng in a food product would have the desired cognitive effect.




3.Anti-inflammatory effects

Ginsenosides may have anti-inflammatory effects, according to experimental results in Journal of Translational Medicine.

Ginseng is often used to reduce inflammation. The researchers suggest that ginsenosides may be responsible for targeting pathways in the immune system that could reduce inflammation.




4.Treatment of erectile dysfunction

Men may take ginseng to treat erectile dysfunction.

A 2002 Korean study revealed that 60 percent of men who took ginseng noticed an improvement in their symptoms. Research published in the British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology also claimed to provide “evidence for the effectiveness of red ginseng in the treatment of erectile dysfunction.”

However, a more recent systematic review has been carried out.

In assessing the effectiveness of red ginseng for treating erectile dysfunction, the review demonstrated that the number of trials, total sample size, and the quality of the experimental methods were not satisfactory for demonstrating ongoing clinical benefit.

Like the sarsaparilla used to make old world root beer, ginseng contains compounds similar to cortisone. These materials stimulate the adrenal cortex, promoting the production of sex hormones, and making ginseng a centuries-long favorite for improving sex drive” Nahai says. Studies suggest that ginseng improves the sex drive in premenopausal women and can help men with erectile dysfunction. Researches aren’t certain how ginseng affects sexual dysfunction, though.

More research is needed to confirm ginseng as a reliable treatment for erectile dysfunction.



5.Flu prevention

Research on the effects of ginseng on mice suggests a possible link between ginseng and the treatment and prevention of influenza and respiratory syncytial virus (RSV).

Findings suggested that red ginseng extract could improve the survival of human lung epithelial cells infected with the influenza virus. However, many studies of the preventive actions of ginseng against viruses were later discredited as unreliable.
Lowering blood sugar

Several studies suggest that ginseng may help lower blood sugar and help treat diabetes. Ginsenosides may affect insulin production in the pancreas and improve insulin resistance using other mechanisms.

More clinical studies and standardization of ginseng root are needed to consider ginseng as a possible complementary therapy for diabetes. This is so that researchers can investigate what specific doses are effective.
Another study has linked ginseng supplementation with improved blood sugar control in type 2 diabetics,” Nahai says. The studies found that when diabetics took ginseng while consuming sugar, they saw less of a relative increase in their blood sugar level. Another study found that ginseng was able to make people more responsive to insulin, another important part of alleviating diabetes since insulin resistance is one of the biggest issues.

Since we’re in the thick of flu season, you’re going to want to stock up on ginseng. Numerous studies have found that it’s effective in preventing the onslaught of certain strains of the flu.
But there are also potential side effects.



6.It combats inflammation

Ginsenosides, the class of plant that ginseng belongs to, may have anti-inflammatory effects, according to experimental results in Journal of Translational Medicine,” Nahai says. The research suggests that these ginsenosides target immune system pathways that ultimately combat inflammation.



7.It’s a potentially natural stimulant for focus and attention

Ginseng acts as a natural stimulant and is prized for its effect on focus and attention; think of it as our earliest pharmacological treatment for ADHD” Nahai says. Although it’s traditionally been revered this way, recent studies have found mixed results. One study, however, discovered that ginseng did have a positive effect on children with ADHD and another study found that it also has a positive impact on Alzheimer’s.



8. It could prevent and alleviate side effects of cancer.

Nuhai says, “Research has linked a positive association of ginseng use in breast cancer survivors. Findings have shown that patients who used ginseng prior to cancer treatment had a higher rate of survival, with use after treatment increasing quality of life.” Other studies have found that the fatigue associated with cancer treatment was lessened through the use of ginseng.


Side Effect:

Not all side effects of ginseng are known. Although ginseng is considered safe to consume, the following side effects have been reported:

    headaches
    sleep proble

    ms
    digestive problems
    changes to blood pressure and blood sugar
    irritability
    nervousness
    blurred vision
    a severe skin reaction
    edema
    diarrhea
    bleeding
    dizziness
    a dry mouth
    a decreased heart rate
    convulsions and seizures
    delirium

Women may also experience swollen breasts and vaginal bleeding.



Interactions

Doctors advise not mixing ginseng with a class of antidepressants called monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs). Taking these antidepressants at the same time as ginseng can cause manic episodes and tremors.

Ginseng can alter the effects of blood pressure, diabetes, and heart medications, including calcium channel blockers such as nifedipine. Never mix ginseng and heart medications without first consulting a doctor.

The herb can also increase the risk of bleeding when taken with blood thinners, such as warfarin or aspirin.

Ginseng may intensify the effects of caffeine and other stimulants, leading to a rapid heartbeat and possible sweating or insomnia. It could also cancel out the painkilling effects of morphine.


Though considered safe, ginseng needs to be thought of as any compound with pharmacological effect: The poison is in the dose,” Nahai says, advocating moderation. “Ginseng is meant to be used as a supplement; an occasional additive, not a part of your daily dietary routine.”

Taking too much of the adaptogen has been linked to everything from headaches to digestive issues, sleep problems, high blood pressure, dizziness, heart palpitations, and more. Nahai says that people with high blood pressure or heart conditions should especially avoid ginseng.

Its environmental impact is something else to consider. And as is the case with any supplement, you should consult your doctor before adding it to your regimen.

If you are introducing adaptogens into your life, here are healthy snack recipes and a hot chocolate recipe to get you through the winter.


        "</string>
    <string name="ginger_details">"GINGER
OTHER NAME(S):

African Ginger, Amomum Zingiber, Ardraka, Black Ginger, Cochin Ginger, Gan Jiang, Gingembre, Gingembre Africain, Gingembre Cochin, Gingembre Indien, Gingembre Jamaïquain, Gingembre Noir, Ginger Essential Oil, Ginger Root, Huile Essentielle de Gingembre, Imber, Indian Ginger, Jamaica Ginger, Jengibre, Jiang, Kankyo, Kanshokyo, Nagara, Race Ginger, Racine de Gingembre, Rhizoma Zingiberi, Rhizoma Zingiberis, Rhizoma Zingiberis Recens, Shen Jiang, Sheng Jiang, Shoga, Shokyo, Shunthi, Srungavera, Sunth, Sunthi, Vishvabheshaja, Zingiber Officinale, Zingiberis Rhizoma, Zingiberis Siccatum Rhizoma, Zinzeberis, Zinziber Officinale, Zinziber Officinalis."
    Overview Information
Ginger is a plant with leafy stems and yellowish green flowers. The ginger spice comes from the roots of the plant. Ginger is native to warmer parts of Asia, such as China, Japan, and India, but now is grown in parts of South American and Africa. It is also now grown in the Middle East to use as medicine and with food.

Ginger is commonly used for many types of nausea and vomiting. It\'s also used for menstrual cramps, osteoarthritis, diabetes, migraine headaches, and other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support many of these uses.

In foods and beverages, ginger is used as a flavoring agent.

In manufacturing, ginger is used as for fragrance in soaps and cosmetics.

One of the chemicals in ginger is also used as an ingredient in laxative, anti-gas, and antacid medications.


How does it work?
Ginger contains chemicals that may reduce nausea and inflammation. Researchers believe the chemicals work primarily in the stomach and intestines, but they may also work in the brain and nervous system to control nausea.
Ginger root has a range of health benefits, including improving digestion, blood sugar levels, and harmful cholesterol levels. Here’s a look at eight of ginger’s benefits and five ways for you to increase your intake.
Ginger is a flowering plant and its official name is Zingiber officinale. The rhizome, more commonly known as the root, is what you are likely familiar with. The root is spicy and peppery in flavor, with loads of medicinal properties. It’s used all over the world in culinary and clinical applications—both for good reason.

Ginger has been called a superfood time and again, but what makes it so powerful? This root has the following eight superpowers.



1. Stimulates Digestion

You know that feeling after you eat a meal when it seems like a brick is in your stomach? You wonder if your body is actually digesting your food or if it’s just going to sit in there forever? Or what about feelings of indigestion with uncomfortable burping and acid reflux? Heartburn is real and painful!

Ginger is your new best friend for supporting everything regarding digestive health. Functional dyspepsia is the clinical term used to describe upper abdominal discomfort like acid reflux that is thought to be related to slowing of the digestive system. Ginger has been shown to be help these issues.

Ginger helps increase the body’s ability to empty food from the stomach more quickly—known as gastric emptying. With this increased motility in the digestive system, it’s less likely that heartburn or indigestion will occur. In fact, one study of healthy participants showed that taking ginger capsules (1200 mg) with a meal stimulates digestion so much that gastric emptying speed was doubled! Imagine the relief that would come from food leaving your stomach twice as quickly.

The more efficient your digestion is, the more energy you will have because researchers have found that approximately 60 percent of your body’s energy goes to metabolism. If ginger can improve digestion, your metabolism will improve and energy will be more available. This is possible because the quicker you can digest your food, the faster you will absorb the vitamins and minerals from the foods you eat. You will also have less undigested food in your digestive tract; food consumes energy when left undigested. So not only does ginger stimulate digestion by improving symptoms of dyspepsia and speeding gastric emptying, but it also benefits your overall energy levels.



2. Lowers Blood Pressure

High blood pressure (known as hypertension) is a common symptom of the standard American diet, which is high in processed foods. According to the Mayo Clinic, when hypertension is left untreated it can lead to damage to your arteries, heart, brain, kidneys, and eyes. Doctors frequently prescribe blood pressure medications to their patients, but what if you could reduce your blood pressure naturally?

Ginger has been shown to improve blood pressure (in conjunction with medication) by acting as a vasodilator—it expands your blood vessels. This is helpful for increasing circulation in the body, which reduces the overall blood pressure throughout the body. Ginger also contains potassium, a mineral that research has found can help lower blood pressure. According to the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA), ginger contains 415 mg of potassium per 100 g. That’s more than a banana (a food known for being high in potassium), which only contains 358 mg per 100 g.



3. Reduces Nausea

Nausea is no fun. Whether it’s from motion sickness, morning sickness, post-surgery effects, chemotherapy, or pregnancy, nausea is not an experience anyone wants. And when you do experience an upset stomach, you’d give anything to make it end! Enter ginger. Ginger has been shown to be an effective remedy for nausea related to pregnancy and chemotherapy.

Ginger has also been found to reduce the amount of nausea you might otherwise experience when feeling seasick. After surgeries, it’s common for some people to experience nausea and vomiting. The good news is that researchers have found ginger to be an “effective means for reducing postoperative nausea and vomiting.” Not only does ginger provide relief from post-surgery nausea, it can also help cancer patients. In a study of both adults and children undergoing chemotherapy treatments, ginger was found to be effective in providing relief from the nausea that accompanies those treatments. Based on the scientific evidence, ginger is definitely worth a try when you’re experiencing nausea of any kind.



4. Reduces Inflammation

Inflammation occurs naturally even in healthy individuals. It’s a natural and healthy response to protect the body from injuries or sickness. However, when inflammation is excessive or chronic, it can be very damaging. In fact, researchers have found that chronic inflammation is at the root of many common diseases such as heart disease, autoimmune disorders, and cancer.

The active constituents in raw ginger—gingerol, shogaol, and paradol—are responsible for many of the natural anti-inflammatory effects that ginger provides. Ginger has been shown to inhibit the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines (small proteins released by cells to communicate with other cells in the body). Pro-inflammatory cytokines are responsible for the upregulation of inflammatory reactions, meaning that these reactions happen more often in the body. This is directly related to increased inflammation in the body. Since ginger has been shown to reduce the levels of inflammation that those pro-inflammatory cytokines can produce, it’s only natural that inflammation will decrease, too. This is a big deal! Because inflammation can run so rampant in the body—especially with a poor diet—ginger is a great way to help reduce the overall amount of inflammation in the body. If you’re experiencing an inflammatory condition, ginger is a natural and powerful anti-inflammatory remedy to try.



5. Antibacterial Properties

If you aren’t convinced of the medicinal properties of ginger yet, you will be now! Researchers have found that ginger is an effective antibacterial for many drug-resistant bacteria in clinical applications. In their study, the researchers stated that “ginger has great potential in the treatment of many microbial diseases [such as Bacillus and E. coli].”

The antibacterial benefits don’t stop there. In oral health, two types of ginger have been shown to inhibit the growth of pathogens that contribute to periodontitis (inflammation of the gums that is caused by gum bacteria). The antibacterial properties that ginger possesses show that food truly is medicine.



6. Blood-Sugar Regulator

Diabetes is the most common disease of the endocrine system. Type 2 diabetes accounts for more than 90 percent of diabetes diagnoses. One of the causes of diabetes is chronic hyperglycemia—the clinical term for high blood sugar. If you can regulate your blood sugar levels, you will be less likely to experience chronic hyperglycemia that can lead to diabetes over time. One study showed that supplementing with ginger reduced fasting blood sugar levels as well as hemoglobin A1c levels.

If you can keep your A1c levels below 5.7 percent, then you are in the normal range. Since ginger reduces blood sugar levels and A1c, it’s safe to say that ginger helps regulate the mind-body system to keep blood sugar levels in check and prevent chronic hyperglycemia.



7. Reduces Menstrual Pains

Many women know how debilitating menstrual pain can be. There are over-the-counter pain medications dedicated to this specific pain, but ginger may also provide relief.

One study found that ginger is as effective as ibuprofen in reducing the pain associated with dysmenorrhea (painful menstruation) in women. Menstrual cramps in the abdomen and lower back are common in dysmenorrhea. That’s great news for women! Next time you experience cramping during your menstrual cycle, give ginger a try.



8. Positively Affects Cholesterol Levels

As stated earlier, ginger is helpful in reducing blood pressure, but it’s also beneficial for cholesterol levels. Ginger has been found to reduce cholesterol levels—specifically reducing low-density lipoproteins (LDL). According to the American Heart Association, “LDL cholesterol is called ’bad’ cholesterol. Think of it as less desirable or even lousy cholesterol, because it contributes to fatty buildups in arteries.” That fatty buildup is known as atherosclerosis and it, it increases the risk of heart attack and stroke.
How to Use Ginger

Knowing all these health benefits of ginger is great, but how can you easily incorporate ginger in your daily routine? Ginger is pretty spicy, so you may not enjoy its taste. Luckily, there are many options for those who love ginger and those who may be new to the root.

    *Fresh ginger root: This is the most potent form of ginger, but also the most versatile. You can slice it and steep it in hot water for tea, mince it into stir-fry dishes, juice it, add it to your smoothies, or even take a slice and suck on it! Dried ginger or ginger juice is great for a mid day snack.
    *Ground ginger: Ground ginger can be used in similar ways to fresh ginger. It can be steeped in hot water for tea or added to your favorite recipes. Powdered ginger is also great to use for baking.
    *Ginger capsules: This is the easiest way to get ginger into your diet—especially if you aren’t a fan of the taste! Ginger capsules, or ginger supplements, are simple. The ground ginger powder is added to a capsule for easy consumption at any time of day.
    *Ginger tea: As mentioned, you can make ginger tea using fresh ginger or ground ginger. But you can also buy ready-to-go ginger extract tea bags at the store. These are great to have on hand if feel nauseated or want to settle your stomach after eating.
    *Ginger chews: Ginger chews are like ginger candies and tend to be more mild in flavor and can be taken anywhere. Make sure to check the ingredients to make sure you’re not consuming unwanted ingredients like corn syrup.
    *Ginger oil: Ginger oil can be taken internally or rubbed topically to treat pain. Ginger essential oil has many soothing properties and is useful to use for massages.

With all the health benefits ginger has to offer and all the different ways you can consume ginger, it’s a no brainer to start incorporating it into your daily life!

"</string>
    <string name="chamomile_details">"Here are 13 amazing health benefits of Chamomile tea. Chamomile tea is prepared from dried flowers, and is known to boost immunity as well as reduce stress. It has a stellar reputation for healing, and with good reason.

Chamomile, also referred to as Babune ka Phal in Hindi, has a stellar reputation for healing, and with good reason. It is prepared from dried flowers and it brings an oasis of calm and tranquility," says Mr. Amit Anand, Owner of Mingle Tea. The beautiful Chamomile flower is native to Asia, Europe, Australia and North America, and blooms during the early summer months.Chamomile tea contains Chamazulene, an aromatic chemical compound that possesses anti-inflammatory, analgesic and antispasmodic properties. Whether you\'re overworked or suffering from a cold, "steep a hot cup of Chamomile tea, inhale its wonderful floral fragrance and then see your worries disappear as you sip this magical golden brew," assures Amit. Chamomile tea is a popular beverage across the world, it is steeped with both health and skin benefits that are hard to find in many other teas. The benefits of chamomile tea are in abundance. It is not only soothing and refreshing, but can also be beneficial for you in more than just one way.
We\'ve spoken to health experts and listed 13 remarkable benefits of Chamomile tea.


1. Promotes Sleep and Treats Insomnia

"Chamomile tea relaxes nerves and soothes the nervous system, therefore helping you sleep better. It lacks the addition of caffeine, and is best consumed before sleeping".


2. Boosts Immunity

Many studies have shown that Chamomile tea will not only kick illnesses to the curb, but also work as a great preventive measure. "It fights harmful bacteria, and has the ability to boost your immune system.


3. Treats Cold

Suffering from a terrible cold? One of the best benefits of chamomile tea comes into play here. Consider drinking a hot cup of chamomile tea and let it work its magic. You can also inhale steam from Chamomile tea (as shown below) to ease nasal congestion, a runny nose and sore throat.


4. Reduces Muscle Spasms and Period Pain

According to a study published in the Journal of Agriculture and Chemistry, Chamomile tea has pain-relieving and antispasmodic properties. It relaxes the uterus and decreases the production of prostaglandins (hormone-like substances that cause inflammation and pain).


5. Soothes Stomach Ache

According to the National Center for Biotechnology Information, "Chamomile tea has been valued as a digestive relaxant and has been used to treat various gastrointestinal disturbances including flatulence, indigestion, diarrhea, anorexia, motion sickness, nausea and vomiting".


6. Treats Cuts, Wound and Skin Conditions

Did you know that Chamomile tea has been used by the Romans, Greeks and Egyptians to treat wounds and promote healing? This is because the plant Chamomile tea is derived from Matricaria chamomilla L, which has anti inflammatory and antimicrobial properties. It also heals skin conditions such as psoriasis and eczema.


7. Reduces Stress

Today's busy, chaotic world leaves us feeling increasingly anxious and stressed. According to Dietician Anshul Jaibharat, "Chamomile tea is a gentle relaxant and acts as an effective natural sedative, thereby reducing stress."


8. Lightens Skin

Sipping into hot chamomile tea could do wonders for your skin too! This magic potion can be used as a natural skin bleach. Chamomile tea is packed with antioxidants which helps boost your skin health. It lightens the complexion and also gives you that glow you've always wanted.


9. Reduces Acne

Not just the glow, chamomile tea could help end your war with frequent acne break out too. Chamomile tea helps fade spots, eliminate acne scars and fight breakouts, if used topically, due to its anti-inflammatory and antiseptic properties.


10. Anti-Ageing

Chamomile tea is a powerhouse of antioxidants and protects the skin from free-radical damage. It accelerates cell and tissue regeneration, helps tighten the pores and slows down the ageing process.


11. Treats Sunburn

The harmful ultraviolet (UV) rays of the sun can cause various problems for your skin. Chamomile tea is known for its antioxidant, soothing and anti-inflammatory properties. You can brew the tea, chill it thoroughly, soak a towel in it and then apply to the sunburned area.


12. Reduces Under-Eye Dark Circles

Suparna Trikha, India's leading beauty expert says, "Never throw away Chamomile tea bags after using them, and refrigerate them instead. You can place the chilled tea bag over your eyes (especially after doing an eye massage) to lighten the eye area dramatically and reduce puffiness. You will find an instant difference in the way your eyes look and feel".



13. Gets Rid of Dandruff

Fed up of dandruff? Drink a cup of chamomile tea. Yes we are serious. Chamomile tea helps eliminate and prevent dandruff, soothe scalp irritation and promote healthy healthy. You can use it as a final rinse after washing your hair. It's that simple."</string>

    <string name="garlic_details">"This tasty, fragrant veggie does more than make your pasta sauce delicious. Garlic is loaded with good-for-you vitamins and minerals like manganese, selenium, vitamin C, vitamin B6, and other antioxidants, including allicin. The health benefits of garlic have been recognized for centuries, ever since the ancient Greek physician Hippocrates prescribed it to treat all kinds of illnesses. Now modern medicine is embracing garlic’s healing properties too. A recent study reports that eating garlic may work to relax blood vessels and increase blood flow. So grab the freshest garlic cloves you can find and add them to your daily diet to reap these benefits for your body.


1. Better Blood Pressure
Garlic has anti-inflammatory benefits and helps blood flow more easily through the body. Several studies found that blood pressure was lowered by 10% when the participant took garlic supplements. Keep in mind that the supplement doses are fairly high—600 to 1,500 mg of aged garlic extract. That’s the equivalent of roughly four cloves of garlic a day, so start chopping.


2. Lower Cholesterol
Garlic can also reduce cardiovascular disease risk by lowering your cholesterol. A group of study participants that took a garlic supplement saw their cholesterol levels go down over a period of five months. The key here is commitment. Like many natural remedies, it takes a while for the benefits of garlic to kick in, because you have to let the vitamins and minerals build up in your body. But adding garlic to your daily routine is a healthy way to develop a lifelong habit that can benefit your health year after year.


3. Reduced Risk of Heart Disease
Garlic is a natural at reducing heart disease risk because it lowers cholesterol and blood pressure. It’s also great at reducing your risk of heart disease by relaxing hardened blood vessels and preventing platelet aggregation. How does it work? Garlic increases production of nitric oxide which keeps blood vessels relaxed. It also prevents platelets from binding to proteins, which reduces blood clots. When it comes to heart disease help, garlic’s got you covered.


4. Garlic for Colds and Flu
Digested garlic helps boost the immune system and reduces the severity and length of cold and flu symptoms. One study showed that taking a daily garlic supplement reduced the number of colds participants experienced by 63%. Studies have also reported that the average length of cold symptoms were reduced from five days to a day and a half. If you like garlic, try adding more to your meals when you feel a cold coming on.


5. Better Athletic Performance
Ancient cultures used garlic to enhance the performance and reduce the fatigue of people doing physical labor. Eventually, the Olympic athletes in Greece started using garlic to enhance their athletic ability. Now modern athletes (and regular folks too) are using it to reduce exercise-induced fatigue. Some studies have shown people with heart disease who took garlic oil for six weeks improved their peak heart rate by 12% and could exercise longer without feeling as tired. If you like to stay fit and love garlic, add a little more to your daily diet and see if you get an endurance boost.


6. Stronger Bones
There is some evidence that garlic can help reduce bone loss by increasing estrogen in females, which can be a big win for your bone health after menopause. Adding a daily dose of garlic could help reduce your risk of osteoporosis and osteoarthritis. You still need to include other healthy foods to make a real impact on bone density—dairy products, green leafy vegetables, fish, and nuts are all good choices. But it’s easy to season your salmon and spinach dinner with garlic for some extra oomph.


7. Improved Memory
Damage from free radicals contributes to aging, but garlic contains a powerful antioxidant to help battle that—S-allyl cysteine. This antioxidant shows promise in protecting against brain damage and keeping your brain functioning better as you age. It works by increasing your brain’s blood flow thanks to garlic’s ability to lower cholesterol and blood pressure. This means a reduced risk of brain disorders like dementia and Alzheimer’s disease.


8. Super Skin
Garlic is a superfood because it has so many beneficial properties: antioxidant, antibacterial and antifungal. Which adds up to big benefits for your skin. Got acne? Rub raw garlic over your bumps to kill bacteria. Just be careful and don’t overdo it if you have sensitive skin. Garlic’s antioxidant qualities come to the rescue to protect your skin and prevent damage from free radicals. Using a topical garlic extract over time may have anti-aging effects because garlic helps increase the growth and longevity of skin cells. Long live garlic!
        "</string>
    <string name="ashoka_details">"The beautiful ashoka tree has many gifts to offer us. From improving complexion to relieving pain, the tree is versatile. There is so much to know about this woman-friendly tree.

Why do you think I said woman-friendly? Read on and find out.


    Table Of Contents

    About Ashoka Tree
    Why The Tree Is Woman Friendly
    Benefits of Ashoka Tree


About Ashoka Tree

Primarily a rainforest tree, the Ashoka has luscious foliage and beautiful orange-yellow flowers. The flower bunches are bright, heavy and fragrant. The tree is found in the Indian subcontinent, particularly close to the foothills of the Himalayas as well as the Western Ghats.

Ashoka tree is considered sacred throughout Nepal, India, and Sri Lanka. It has strong religious associations, with Buddhists and Hindus including the tree in their cultural traditions. Ashoka tree finds prominence in ancient Hindu mythology, art, sculpture and even Ramayana. It is said that Buddha was born under an Ashoka tree.


Why The Tree Is Woman Friendly

I called the Ashoka tree a woman’s friend because of its reputation to keep a woman youthful. Apparently, the tree can drive away a woman’s pain and sorrow through its ability to gift good health. Incidentally, the word Ashoka is translated as ‘no grief’ or ‘without sorrow’ in Sanskrit.

The tree has many medicinal qualities (1). Needless to say, dried stem, bark and flowers from the tree find applications in many areas. Tonics and capsules made from seeds, flowers, and bark, are widely used in India for treating a variety of health conditions.



Female Reproductive Health


Menstrual Problems

As an effective uterine tonic, Ashoka is hard to beat. It tones the uterus, easing heavy menstrual flow and relieving discomfort. The bark of the Ashoka tree is rich in flavonoids, tannins and glycosides that work as a uterine sedative that has a direct impact on the fibres present in the muscles of the uterus.

The bark also contains natural phytoestrogens which help to regulate the menstrual cycle, stimulating the uterus to normalise menstrual flow.

Ashoka can be effectively used to aid with a number of uncomfortable menstrual disorders such as; Premenstrual Syndrome (PMS), Amenorrhea (absent periods), Dysmenorrhea (painful periods) and Menorrhagia (heavy and prolonged menstrual bleeding).


Menopause

Recent studies have confirmed the presence of quercetin, beta-sitosterol and luteolin, phytoestrogens that support healthy hormonal function during the transition into the menopause. One particular study found that the bark exerts a balancing effect on artificially elevated oestrogen levels, exhibiting adaptogenic qualities that are referred to in Ayurveda as “herbal intelligence”. Furthermore, it can support the healthy production of oestrogen and progesterone only when it is needed.

The hormonal balance that is promoted by this herb makes it effective against many menopause symptoms including; hot flushes, night sweats, sleep problems, mood swings and weight gain.


Infertility

Ashoka is considered particularly effective for female infertility and endometriosis. One study, published in "Complementary Therapies in Clinical Practice", identified Ashoka as one of the herbal remedies used by traditional healers in remote areas of India to successfully treat “reproductive disorders”.

An article published in the "Journal of Clinical and Diagnostic Research", explored some of the infertility treatments popular amongst Indian women. It said, “The drug of choice for female infertility is Ashoka, by its astringent taste and cold potency, it strengthens the uterus. It stops the bleeding by contracting the uterine blood vessels and promoting uterine muscular contraction. It stimulates the uterine function by stimulating the (endometrium) and the ovarian functions”.

It is important to note that diet and lifestyle were also addressed during treatment. The success of Ashoka in the treatment of infertility in women may be linked to the herb’s ability to successfully treat endometrios - one of the leading causes of infertility in women.


Benefits of Ashoka Tree

1. Gynecological Problems

Ashoka tree is popularly used in the treatment of gynecological problems and menstrual disorders in women. The herb acts as a tonic for uterine muscles and endometrium, controlling spasms and abdominal pain.

It is taken to treat and alleviate symptoms of irregular menstrual cycles, dysmenorrhoea, amenorrhoea, leucorrhoea, fibroids, cysts and other related disorders.



2. Skin Complexion

The Ashoka herb can naturally improve the skin’s complexion. It helps in blood purification and prevention of further skin allergies. As it removes toxins, it serves to clear the complexion. Moreover, extracts from the tree can also be used to soothe burns and skin irritations.


3. Pain Relief

Ashoka tree has pain relieving properties and can be used as an analgesic safely. Use the paste of the bark for joint pains and experience relief.


4. Internal Bleeding

The herb can treat internal bleeding and hemorrhages effectively. The Ashoka flower extract is used to treat hemorrhagic dysentery. Drink a few drops of water mixed with crushed Ashoka flower for treating the condition.


5. Diabetes

Similarly, dried flowers from Ashoka tree are helpful for diabetics. Consume tonics or decoctions regularly to benefit from the tree’s offerings.


6. Piles

Ashoka tree extracts are used in the treatment of internal piles and bleeding due to piles. The herbal supplements, prepared from the bark, are made into decoctions and consumed.


7. Infections

Ward away fungal and bacterial infections with the tree’s bark. The bark is composed of properties that purify the body and eliminate infections.


8. Worms

This herb can treat worm infections as well. Clear your stomach of worm infestations by consuming leaves or bark of the Ashoka tree. It not only relieves pain, but also reduces bloating.


9. Diarrhea

Ashoka tree and its offerings will treat your diarrhea without any side effects. Use the Ashoka tree leaves, flowers and bark as a tonic and feel the relief. It also purifies the blood in the process.


10. Kidney Stones

Ashoka tree seed power is a natural method to control kidney stones. Have the powder with water, which will decrease your risk of painful stone extraction.

The tree is revered for its healing properties. However, it has only one contraindication. Ashoka tree extracts are not meant for consumption by pregnant women as they are abortive in nature.


"</string>
    <string name="triphala_details">"India is the land of Ayurveda, and people truly believe in the power of herbal preparations in treating various medical conditions. Since time immemorial, Triphala, better known as Triphala churna, has proven its efficacy in treating various health ailments. With people becoming more aware of the cons of modern-day allopathic medicines, herbal preparations are gaining popularity, and people are opting for these herbal preparations to feel better. Here is how you can benefit by taking this herbal remedy.


        What is Triphala Churna?

Triphala means three fruits. Therefore, Triphala churna is not made of one single herbal ingredient, but a combination of three fruits. The three fruits include Haritaki or Terminalia chebula, Bibhitaki or Terminalia bellirica, and Amla or Emblica Officinalis. These fruits are completely dried, powdered and then mixed in the correct amounts to make the Triphala churna.

        What are the Benefits of Triphala Churna?

Some of the many benefits of Triphala powder include:


1. Helpful in Weight Loss

Excess weight is one of the most dreaded health demons and also the foundation of many other health problems. If you are looking for easier ways to keep your weight under check, Triphala may help you in achieving that. Taking Triphala churna aids the secretion of cholecystokinin in the body. Cholecystokinin is a hormone that is helpful in quickly signalling the brain that the stomach is full. This makes you feel fuller and also help you feel satiated. You can take a tablespoon of this churna three times a day with warm water to protect yourself from obesity issues. It is also effective in reducing excess belly fat.


2. Acts as a Detoxifier

The toxins in our body keep piling up as we keep eating unhealthy food items, and these toxins are responsible for making us sick. Therefore, it is important to detoxify our body and get rid of these harmful toxins. Triphala can be used to avail this health benefit too. This churna not only helps in getting rid of all the deadly toxins from your body but is also good for your skin by making it glow. You can make a decoction by mixing a tablespoon of this powder in a glass of water. Add crushed ginger and boil the decoction until it is reduced to half. Strain the decoction and add lemon juice. Drink when warm for maximum benefits. Ideally, this decoction should be had on an empty stomach; you may take this for at least a week to help your body get rid of the toxins.


3. Cures Digestive Issues

If you are dealing with any kind of digestive issues, you can consume Triphala to feel better. This churna not only helps in easing the bowel movements but also regulates the bowel movements due to its laxative properties. If you’re feeling bloated, your tummy is feeling heavy, or you have loose motions, you can safely consume this powder in the morning with lots of water. This churna also takes care of your digestive health by strengthening rectal muscles, relieving flatulence and keeping the stomach clean.


4. Helps in Fighting Infections and Enhances Immunity

Consuming this powdered medicine is a great way of enhancing your immunity. The combination of three fruits is an effective herbal medicine in improving one’s immunity, thus protecting the body against infections that may be caused due to Staphylococcus bacteria, E.Coli etc. By aiding the blood circulation and nourishing the body with essential nutrients, Triphala helps the body in building a better immune system, which is also effective in protecting the body from various infections.


5. Beneficial in Maintaining Oral Hygiene

Many of us might suffer from dental issues such as dental plaque, gingivitis, gum diseases, mouth ulcers and other such dental disorders. This herbal powder is loaded with antimicrobial properties. In a study, it has been proven that a mouth rinse with Triphala extracts showed effective results in dealing with dental issues such as gingivitis and plaque. Also, in a study, it was established that Triphala churna was better in dealing with gum issues in comparison other commercial toothpaste.


6. Beneficial for Eye Health

This herbal remedy is a boon for the eyes and can be aptly called the tonic for maintaining good eye health. It not only helps in keeping your eyes healthy but it also aids in maintaining a sharp vision. Triphala is also effective in keeping various eye troubles or infections such as glaucoma, conjunctivitis, cataract etc. at bay. You may consume the churna orally, or you may use it as an eyewash to help soothe the eye infection. People who spend more time in front of their computer screens, phones or other such electronics may suffer from a condition known as ‘computer vision syndrome’. In a study, it has been proven that Triphala eye drops helped in reducing the symptoms of computer vision syndrome. You may soak 1 to 2 teaspoons of this churna in warm water and let it sit overnight. In the morning, you may strain the water and wash your eyes with this water.


7. Helpful in Treating Gastric Ulcers

Triphala is also beneficial in treating gastric ulcers. This is because when this churna is taken on a regular basis, it reduces the internal as well as external inflammation. It also helps in restoring the enzymes in the body that keeps the toxins away from the body and helps in strengthening the mucous membrane of the stomach.


8. Helps in Treating Urinary Tract Infections

UTI or urinary tract infection can affect both men and women. This painful condition may sometimes become hard to cure, especially when the bacteria causing the infection become immune to the antibiotic medicines or do not respond well to the conventional methods of treatment. During such situations, you may consider using Triphala churna to cure the urinary tract infection. This herbal combination is not only safe and has no side-effects, but it is also has shown promising results on various drug-resistant bacteria.


9. Helpful in Reducing Joint and Bone Pains

If you are suffering from bone or joint pain, Triphala may offer the solution to your problem. This churna is effective in maintaining good bone health by providing ample nutrients to the body. It also aids flushing of excessive amounts of uric acid from the body, which is responsible for bone and joint inflammation. Whenever you experience a joint or bone pain such as gout, arthritis, joint pain etc., you may mix a teaspoon of this powder in some warm water and take this decoction to ease your pain.


10. Helpful in Healing Wounds

The churna has anti-microbial and anti-inflammatory properties, and thus this herbal remedy works wonders in healing various wounds and also aids the recovery process.


11. Effective in Regulating Blood Pressure

Irregular blood pressure may lead to various kinds of health troubles. However, consuming Triphala on a regular basis is beneficial in regulating your blood pressure levels and thus keeping off various health troubles.


12. Helpful in Stimulating Hair Growth

There are many benefits of Triphala churna for hair, and one of the benefits includes stimulating hair growth. Therefore, if you are battling growth issues with your hair, Triphala may be your one-stop solution. You can either consume this herbal remedy orally or make a paste with this churna by adding some water and then applying it on your hair. Triphala is loaded with emollient properties, which are helpful in locking the moisture and thus preventing alopecia. The topical application or oral consumption, both help in aiding the hair growth.


13. Keeps Your Hormones in Place

It is very important to have a healthy hormonal balance in the body because any kind of hormonal imbalance may lead to health complications. Therefore, if you are experiencing painful periods or irregular periods, consuming Triphala churna may prove to be beneficial in providing a remedy to your problem. You may consume a teaspoonful of this churna with a glass of warm water before retiring for the night or two hours after your dinner to regulate your hormonal balance.


14. Helpful in Reducing Dark Circles

Are you fighting dark circles under your eyes? Well, gone are the days when panda eyes were something that you had to live with because now you have Triphala to the rescue. Puffy eyes, dark circles, tired eyes and other such under-eye issues can get cured by using Triphala. You can take eyewash made with Triphala. This not only reduces dark circles and puffiness but it also helps in keeping good eye health.


15. Helpful in Curing Bad Breath

Bad or foul breath can be a big turn off and make you feel embarrassed too. Say no to bad breath with this miraculous churna. You can add honey to the churna and lick this mixture for warding off bad breath. On the other hand, you can also gargle with water in which a teaspoon of powder is mixed to keep bad breath at bay.


16. Beneficial for Kids

Triphala churna not only offers ample benefits for the adults but it also renders many benefits to the children. Young children do not have a very strong immunity, and thus this churna is not only good to improve the immunity in children, but it is also effective in fighting various kinds of common infections that kids usually suffer from such as a cough, cold, fever etc. You may give Triphala with milk, water or mixed with some honey. If your baby is less than 12 months, you should not give more than a pinch of this churna. For older kids, a teaspoon may be given.



17. Helpful in Motion Sickness and Curing Dizziness

Many of us may be dreading travelling because of the sheer thought of motion sickness. However, taking this churna may help you overcome your dizziness or motion sickness. Every time you feel sick, you may take a few grams of this churna mixed with honey to feel better. On the other hand, if you experience any kind of dizziness on a regular basis, you may take this mixture every day in the morning.


18. Helpful in Managing Diabetes

If you are suffering from diabetes, you may take Triphala to manage your blood sugar levels. This is an alternative treatment method that makes use of herbal remedies in balancing the sugar in the blood. This remedy not only regulates the sugar but it also aids in bringing it down and thus works as an effective treatment for managing diabetes.


19. Helpful in Boosting Heart Health

Triphala acts as a tonic for your heart because it helps in improving or boosting heart health. This happens because by consuming this churna your blood circulation improves, your bad cholesterol goes down and your blood pressure gets regulated. Together all these factors help in improving the overall heart health and thus keeping the heart healthy. Therefore, in order to have good cardio health, you may like to give Triphala a try.



20. Helps in Skin Rejuvenation

Looking for baby soft and smooth skin? If yes, then look no further and opt for Triphala for a healthy skin glow and to obtain that unbeatable freshness. This churna has antioxidants in it, which helps in fighting various skin infections and also reduces acne-causing bacteria. If you have dry or flaky skin, you can benefit greatly by using Triphala because it has ample amounts of emollient properties that helps in keeping the skin soft and moist.

The above-mentioned are some of the many benefits of consuming Triphala.


How to Make Triphala Powder at Home?

Why procure the churna from the market when you can safely make it at home. All you have to do is procure the right ingredients. Here is what you need and what you should do to make a perfect Triphala churna.



Ingredients:

To make this ayurvedic remedy, you require:

    Amla- 80 grams
    Baheda- 40 grams
    Harad- 20 grams
    Mortar and pestle

Method:

The method of making this churna is very simple and easy.

    Take all the ingredients in the right amounts and dry them completely.
    Once all the ingredients are dried up, take them one by one and ground them into a fine powder using mortar and pestle.
    Sieve the powder and mix all the powdered ingredients well.
    Store them in an airtight container.


Ways to Take Triphala Churna for Best Results

Some of the benefits of this churna were given in the above section, and now we shall explain how you should take this churna for the best results:


1. Take It In a Form of Tea

You may have tea made from this powder and drink it to feel hale and hearty. You can take a teaspoon of this churna and boil in water. Strain and add honey for some taste. You may safely consume this tea two to three times a day.

2. Triphala Face Pack

Now achieving a blemish-free glowing skin is not that difficult. All you need to do is use Triphala to feel radiant. You can take a spoonful of this powder and mix it nicely with some coconut oil. Apply liberally over your face and neck. Leave this pack for approximately 10 to 15 minutes and then rinse off with warm water. Your skin will be soft, supple and with regular use, it will also become blemish-free.

3. Triphala Eyewash

As stated above, Triphala is beneficial in keeping your eyes beautiful and healthy. You can also make eyewash using this churna. All you have to do it mix this powder in a glass of water and leave it overnight. In the morning, you can strain and use the water for washing your eyes to keep them healthy and safe from any kinds of infections.

4. Triphala with Lemon and Honey

Some people may find it difficult to gulp down Triphala because of this strange taste. For those of you who face issues in consuming it in powdered form, you may mix lemon juice and honey to make it palatable. However, ideally, you should consume the churna with warm water without any additives to avail the maximum benefits. Alternatively, you may also avail benefits of Triphala churna by taking it with milk.

5. Triphala In The Form Of Capsules And Tablets

Another option for people who cannot consume it in a powdered form is to take this herbal preparation in the form of tablets or capsules. There are many renowned herbal brands that make such capsules and tablets. Also, it is easier to consume Triphala in this form. However, ensure that you do not consume it is large amounts or else it may lead to complications.
Warning

Triphala churna is one of the safest ayurvedic remedies that have been in use for a long time. However, there are certain considerations you must exercise for achieving the most from this herbal remedy. Here are certain precautionary measures that you should consider before taking this herbal preparation:

    Though Triphala is good for people suffering from diabetes, however, it is suggested that you consult your doctor before taking this herbal remedy on a regular basis.

    Refrain from taking more than the recommended dosage or as prescribed by your doctor. More than required amounts may lead to dehydration.

    Babies may also benefit from this herbal remedy, but you should not give them more than a pinch of this powder. This is because more amounts of Triphala may make your baby’s tummy upset and cause diarrhoea or other tummy issues.

    This churna is loaded with fibre, and if more than required amount is consumed, it may lead to bloating. Also, you should take smaller dosages of this churna if you are suffering from gastric issues.

    A pregnant and breastfeeding mother should not take this herbal remedy. This is because Triphala may cause downward energy flow, which may lead to natural abortion or miscarriage. This herbal medicine can also pass through the breast milk to the baby; therefore, breastfeeding mothers should avoid taking it.


FAQs

Here are some commonly or frequently asked questions about consuming Triphala churna:

1. Can Triphala Churna Interact with Medications?

Whenever you are taking Triphala, you must ensure that there is at least a gap of 12 hours before you take any other medication. If you do not follow this gap, there are chances that this churna interacts with your other medications. The best way to clear confusion is to consult your doctor and ask how you can take your medication if you are taking this churna too.

2. Is there an Effective Time to Take Triphala Churna?

No, there is no particular time or for that matter season when you should consume this churna. You should consume this herbal medicine on a regular basis to avail maximum benefits. However, the best way to take this churna is on an empty stomach with some warm water. Alternatively, this churna can be had two hours before bedtime with some warm water. The best way to get the optimum benefits is by consuming this herbal preparation in the prescribed amounts.

Ayurveda is flooded with many effective herbal medicines that can be used to cure many health problems. You can safely consume this remedy and bid goodbye to some of your serious medical issues. However, it is suggested that you consult an ayurvedic doctor before taking this herbal remedy.

"</string>
    <string name="tulsi_details">"Tulsi or Holy basil is a widely known herb in the family Lamiaceae. It is native to India and vastly cultivated throughout Southeast Asia.

Tulsi has proved to be highly effective in protecting our body from various infections and diseases of heart, liver, skin, kidney etc. [1]So, Tulsi is rightly called the ‘Queen of Herbs’.

Tulsi has a special place in Ayurveda as well as the home of Hindus in India. It is considered sacred by Hindus and worshipped by them. Three main types of Tulsi are seen growing in India:

    Bright green leaves called Ram Tulsi
    Purplish green leaves called Krishna Tulsi
    Common wild Vana Tulsi.

Nutritional Value:

Tulsi leaves are rich in vitamins A, C and K and minerals like calcium, magnesium, phosphorus, iron and potassium. It also has a good amount of protein and fibre.
11 Research-Backed Benefits of Tulsi are:

    Natural Immunity Booster:

Tulsi is rich in Vitamin C and zinc. It thus acts as a natural immunity booster and keeps infections at bay. It has immense anti-bacterial, anti-viral and anti-fungal properties which protect us from a variety of infections. Tulsi leaves extract increases the T helper cells and natural killer cells activity, boosting the immune system.[2]

Also Read: 7 Tips to Boost Immunity.

    Reduces Fever (antipyretic) &amp; Pain(analgesic):

Tulsi has anti-bacterial and anti-viral properties which help to fight infections, thus reducing fever. The fresh juice of Tulsi taken with black pepper powder cures periodic fevers. Tulsi leaves boiled with powdered cardamom(elaichi) in half a litre of water and mixed with sugar and milk, is also effective in reducing temperature. [3]

Eugenol, a terpene with pain-relieving properties found in Tulsi reduces aches in the body.

    Reduces Cold, Cough &amp; Other Respiratory Disorders:

Camphene, cineole, and eugenol present in Tulsi helps to reduce cold and congestion in the chest.

Juice of Tulsi leaves mixed with honey and ginger is effective in bronchitis, asthma, influenza, cough and cold.[4]

    Reduces Stress &amp; Blood Pressure:

Tulsi contains compounds Ocimumosides A and B. These compounds reduce stress and balance the neurotransmitters serotonin and dopamine in the brain.[5]Anti-inflammatory properties of Tulsi reduce inflammation and blood pressure.[6]

    Anti-cancer properties:

Phytochemicals present in Tulsi have strong antioxidant property. Thus, they help in protecting us from skin, liver, oral and lung cancers.[7]

    Good for Heart Health:

Tulsi has a profound effect on treatment and prevention of cardiovascular diseases by means of lowering blood lipid content, suppressing ischemia and stroke, reducing hypertension, and also due to its higher antioxidant properties.[8] Read more about tips for a healthy heart.

    Good for Diabetes Patients:

Extract of Tulsi leaves has shown to lower blood glucose levels in patients with type 2 Diabetes.[9]

    Useful in Kidney stones &amp; Gouty Arthritis:

Tulsi detoxifies the body and has diuretic properties. It decreases the level of uric acid in the body, which is the main reason why kidney stones are formed. Reduction in uric acid levels also provides relief to patients suffering from Gout.

    Useful in Gastrointestinal Disorders:

Tulsi leaves help to cure indigestion and loss of appetite. They are also used for the treatment of flatulence and bloating.

    Good for Skin &amp; Hair:

Tulsi helps clear out the skin of blemishes and acne. It is rich in antioxidants, and that helps it to prevent premature ageing. Tulsi also strengthens our hair roots, thus preventing hair loss.

Antifungal properties of Tulsi prevent the development of fungus and dandruff.



    Acts as an Insect Repellent:

For centuries, the dried Tulsi leaves have been mixed with stored grains to repel insects.
How to Consume Tulsi?

    Consume Tulsi leaves raw, plucked fresh from the plant, add it in your tea or make kadha out of it.
    Tulsi tea: To make tulsi tea, boil 1 cup of water and pour it over 1 tsp of fresh tulsi leaves, 1/2 tsp of dried tulsi leaves, or 1/3 tsp of tulsi powder. Cover the water in a pot or mug and let it seep for 15-20 minutes. Then strain the leaves, add honey if desired, and enjoy.
    Tulsi powders and supplements are also available in the market for consumption.

Side Effects of Consuming Tulsi That You Must Know:

    Tulsi may affect the reproductive capacity of women who are trying to conceive..
    Some people experience nausea or diarrhoea when they first add tulsi tea to their diet, so its best to start with small quantities and increase your consumption over time.
    Tulsi may lower blood sugar and should be used with caution in people who have diabetes and are on blood-sugar-lowering medication.
"</string>
    <string name="alovera_details">"Aloe vera is a popular medicinal plant that people have used for thousands of years.

Aloe vera, or Aloe barbadensis, is a thick, short-stemmed plant that stores water in its leaves. It is best known for treating skin injuries, but it also has several other uses that could potentially benefit health.

This article lists eight potential health benefits of aloe vera. It also covers some of the risks associated with use.\n\n

1. It contains healthful plant compounds
 The cosmetic, pharmaceutical, and food industries use aloe vera extensively, and the plant has an estimated annual market value of $13 billion globally.

Aloe vera is known for its thick, pointed, and fleshy green leaves, which may grow to about 12–19 inches (30–50 centimeters) in length.

Each leaf contains a slimy tissue that stores water, and this makes the leaves thick. This water filled tissue is the “gel” that people associate with aloe vera products.

The gel contains most of the beneficial bioactive compounds in the plant, including vitamins, minerals, amino acids, and antioxidants.


2. It has antioxidant and antibacterial properties

Antioxidants are important for health. Aloe vera gel contains powerful antioxidants belonging to a large family of substances known as polyphenols.

These polyphenols, along with several other compounds in aloe vera, help inhibit the growth of certain bacteria that can cause infections in humans.

Aloe vera is known for its antibacterial, antiviral, and antiseptic properties. This is part of why it may help heal wounds and treat skin problems.



3. It accelerates wound healing

People most often use aloe vera as a topical medication, rubbing it onto the skin rather than consuming it. In fact, it has a long history of use in treating sores, and particularly burns, including sunburn.

The United States Pharmacopeia describe aloe vera preparations as a skin protectant as early as 1810–1820.

Studies suggest that it is an effective topical treatment for first and second degree burns.

For example, a review of experimental studies found that aloe vera could reduce the healing time of burns by around 9 days compared with conventional medication. It also helped prevent redness, itching, and infections.

The evidence for aloe vera helping heal other types of wound is inconclusive, but the research is promising.


 4. It reduces dental plaque

Tooth decay and diseases of the gum are very common health problems. One of the best ways to prevent these conditions is to reduce the buildup of plaque, or bacterial biofilms, on the teeth.

In a mouth rinse study of 300 healthy people, researchers compared 100% pure aloe vera juice with the standard mouthwash ingredient chlorhexidine.

After 4 days of use, the aloe vera mouth rinse appeared to be just as effective as chlorhexidine in reducing dental plaque.

Another study found similar benefits of aloe vera mouth rinse over a 15- to 30-day period.

Aloe vera is effective in killing the plaque-producing bacterium Streptococcus mutans in the mouth, as well as the yeast Candida albicans.


5. It helps treat canker sores

Many people experience mouth ulcers, or canker sores, at some point in their lives. These usually form underneath the lip, inside the mouth, and last for about a week.

Studies have shown that aloe vera treatment can accelerate the healing of mouth ulcers.

For example, in a 7-day study of 180 people with recurrent mouth ulcers, applying an aloe vera patch to the area was effective in reducing the size of the ulcers.

However, it did not outperform the conventional ulcer treatment: corticosteroids.

In another study, aloe vera gel not only accelerated the healing of mouth ulcers, it also reduced the pain associated with them.


6. It reduces constipation

Aloe vera may also help treat constipation.

This time it is the latex, not the gel, that provides the benefits. The latex is a sticky yellow residue present just under the skin of the leaf.

The key compound responsible for this effect is called aloin, or barbaloin, which has well-established laxative effects.

However, people have raised concerns about safety with frequent use. For this reason, aloe latex has not been available in the U.S. as an over-the-counter medication since 2002.

Contrary to popular belief, aloe vera does not appear to be effective against other digestive conditions, such as irritable bowel syndrome or inflammatory bowel disease. Learn more here.\n\n


7. It may improve skin and prevent wrinkles

There is some preliminary evidence to suggest that topical aloe vera gel can slow aging of the skin.

In a 2009 study of 30 females over the age of 45, taking oral aloe vera gel increased collagen production and improved skin elasticity over a 90-day period.

Reviews also suggest that aloe vera could help the skin retain moisture and improve skin integrity, which could benefit dry skin conditions.



8. It lowers blood sugar levels

People sometimes use aloe vera as a remedy for diabetes. This is because it may enhance insulin sensitivity and help improve blood sugar management.

For example, a review of eight studies found that aloe vera could have benefits for people with prediabetes or type 2 diabetes due to its effects on glycemic control.

However, the quality of the existing studies is not ideal, so scientists do not currently recommend using aloe vera for this purpose.


Risks

Aloe vera is a safe remedy with few known side effects.

The National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) say that topical use is likely safe.

That said, the oral use of aloe vera may cause stomach cramps or diarrhea due to its laxative effects. There have also been some reports of liver damage associated with long-term aloe vera supplement use.

The NCCIH also report that nondecolorized whole leaf extract of aloe vera seems to be associated with cancer risk in rats.
Summary

Aloe vera has a range of therapeutic properties, especially as an ointment for the skin and gums.

People can use bottled aloe vera gel or take it directly from the leaf of an aloe plant. Aloe vera juice has different uses to aloe vera gel.

Oral options should contain decolorized whole leaf extract of aloe vera to minimize risk.

A person should always speak to a doctor before using aloe products to treat a condition."</string>

    <string name="title_activity_details">DetailsActivity</string>
    <string name="large_text">
        "Material is the metaphor.\n\n"

        "A material metaphor is the unifying theory of a rationalized space and a system of motion."
        "The material is grounded in tactile reality, inspired by the study of paper and ink, yet "
        "technologically advanced and open to imagination and magic.\n"
        "Surfaces and edges of the material provide visual cues that are grounded in reality. The "
        "use of familiar tactile attributes helps users quickly understand affordances. Yet the "
        "flexibility of the material creates new affordances that supercede those in the physical "
        "world, without breaking the rules of physics.\n"
        "The fundamentals of light, surface, and movement are key to conveying how objects move, "
        "interact, and exist in space and in relation to each other. Realistic lighting shows "
        "seams, divides space, and indicates moving parts.\n\n"

        "Bold, graphic, intentional.\n\n"

        "The foundational elements of print based design typography, grids, space, scale, color, "
        "and use of imagery guide visual treatments. These elements do far more than please the "
        "eye. They create hierarchy, meaning, and focus. Deliberate color choices, edge to edge "
        "imagery, large scale typography, and intentional white space create a bold and graphic "
        "interface that immerse the user in the experience.\n"
        "An emphasis on user actions makes core functionality immediately apparent and provides "
        "waypoints for the user.\n\n"

        "Motion provides meaning.\n\n"

        "Motion respects and reinforces the user as the prime mover. Primary user actions are "
        "inflection points that initiate motion, transforming the whole design.\n"
        "All action takes place in a single environment. Objects are presented to the user without "
        "breaking the continuity of experience even as they transform and reorganize.\n"
        "Motion is meaningful and appropriate, serving to focus attention and maintain continuity. "
        "Feedback is subtle yet clear. Transitions are efﬁcient yet coherent.\n\n"

        "3D world.\n\n"

        "The material environment is a 3D space, which means all objects have x, y, and z "
        "dimensions. The z-axis is perpendicularly aligned to the plane of the display, with the "
        "positive z-axis extending towards the viewer. Every sheet of material occupies a single "
        "position along the z-axis and has a standard 1dp thickness.\n"
        "On the web, the z-axis is used for layering and not for perspective. The 3D world is "
        "emulated by manipulating the y-axis.\n\n"

        "Light and shadow.\n\n"

        "Within the material environment, virtual lights illuminate the scene. Key lights create "
        "directional shadows, while ambient light creates soft shadows from all angles.\n"
        "Shadows in the material environment are cast by these two light sources. In Android "
        "development, shadows occur when light sources are blocked by sheets of material at "
        "various positions along the z-axis. On the web, shadows are depicted by manipulating the "
        "y-axis only. The following example shows the card with a height of 6dp.\n\n"

        "Resting elevation.\n\n"

        "All material objects, regardless of size, have a resting elevation, or default elevation "
        "that does not change. If an object changes elevation, it should return to its resting "
        "elevation as soon as possible.\n\n"

        "Component elevations.\n\n"

        "The resting elevation for a component type is consistent across apps (e.g., FAB elevation "
        "does not vary from 6dp in one app to 16dp in another app).\n"
        "Components may have different resting elevations across platforms, depending on the depth "
        "of the environment (e.g., TV has a greater depth than mobile or desktop).\n\n"

        "Responsive elevation and dynamic elevation offsets.\n\n"

        "Some component types have responsive elevation, meaning they change elevation in response "
        "to user input (e.g., normal, focused, and pressed) or system events. These elevation "
        "changes are consistently implemented using dynamic elevation offsets.\n"
        "Dynamic elevation offsets are the goal elevation that a component moves towards, relative "
        "to the component’s resting state. They ensure that elevation changes are consistent "
        "across actions and component types. For example, all components that lift on press have "
        "the same elevation change relative to their resting elevation.\n"
        "Once the input event is completed or cancelled, the component will return to its resting "
        "elevation.\n\n"

        "Avoiding elevation interference.\n\n"

        "Components with responsive elevations may encounter other components as they move between "
        "their resting elevations and dynamic elevation offsets. Because material cannot pass "
        "through other material, components avoid interfering with one another any number of ways, "
        "whether on a per component basis or using the entire app layout.\n"
        "On a component level, components can move or be removed before they cause interference. "
        "For example, a floating action button (FAB) can disappear or move off screen before a "
        "user picks up a card, or it can move if a snackbar appears.\n"
        "On the layout level, design your app layout to minimize opportunities for interference. "
        "For example, position the FAB to one side of stream of a cards so the FAB won’t interfere "
        "when a user tries to pick up one of cards.\n\n"

    </string>
    <!--Banner 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/6300978111
    Interstitial 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/1033173712
    Interstitial Video 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/8691691433
    Rewarded Video 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/5224354917
    Native Advanced 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/2247696110
    Native Advanced Video 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/1044960115-->

    <string name="app_id">ca-app-pub-3940256099942544~3347511713</string>
    <string name="banner_unit_id">ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/6300978111</string>
    <string name="interstitial_unit_id">ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/1033173712</string>

</resources>
