<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Ayurvedic</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="nav_header_title">Ayurvedic</string>
   <!-- <string name="nav_header_subtitle">android.studio@android.com</string>-->
    <string name="nav_header_desc">Navigation header</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Help</string>

    <string name="menu_home">Home</string>
    <string name="menu_gallery">Gallery</string>
    <string name="menu_slideshow">Slideshow</string>
    <string name="menu_tools">Tools</string>
    <string name="menu_share">Share</string>
    <string name="menu_send">Rate us</string>

    <string name="alovera">"ALovera \n\n What are the benefits of aloe vera?"</string>
    <string name="tusli">"Tusli \n\n The Health Benefits of Holy Basil"</string>
    <string name="tulsi_details">"Tulsi or Holy basil is a widely known herb in the family Lamiaceae. It is native to India and vastly cultivated throughout Southeast Asia.

Tulsi has proved to be highly effective in protecting our body from various infections and diseases of heart, liver, skin, kidney etc. [1]So, Tulsi is rightly called the ‘Queen of Herbs’.

Tulsi has a special place in Ayurveda as well as the home of Hindus in India. It is considered sacred by Hindus and worshipped by them. Three main types of Tulsi are seen growing in India:

    Bright green leaves called Ram Tulsi
    Purplish green leaves called Krishna Tulsi
    Common wild Vana Tulsi.

Nutritional Value:

Tulsi leaves are rich in vitamins A, C and K and minerals like calcium, magnesium, phosphorus, iron and potassium. It also has a good amount of protein and fibre.
11 Research-Backed Benefits of Tulsi are:

    Natural Immunity Booster:

Tulsi is rich in Vitamin C and zinc. It thus acts as a natural immunity booster and keeps infections at bay. It has immense anti-bacterial, anti-viral and anti-fungal properties which protect us from a variety of infections. Tulsi leaves extract increases the T helper cells and natural killer cells activity, boosting the immune system.[2]

Also Read: 7 Tips to Boost Immunity.

    Reduces Fever (antipyretic) &amp; Pain(analgesic):

Tulsi has anti-bacterial and anti-viral properties which help to fight infections, thus reducing fever. The fresh juice of Tulsi taken with black pepper powder cures periodic fevers. Tulsi leaves boiled with powdered cardamom(elaichi) in half a litre of water and mixed with sugar and milk, is also effective in reducing temperature. [3]

Eugenol, a terpene with pain-relieving properties found in Tulsi reduces aches in the body.

    Reduces Cold, Cough &amp; Other Respiratory Disorders:

Camphene, cineole, and eugenol present in Tulsi helps to reduce cold and congestion in the chest.

Juice of Tulsi leaves mixed with honey and ginger is effective in bronchitis, asthma, influenza, cough and cold.[4]

    Reduces Stress &amp; Blood Pressure:

Tulsi contains compounds Ocimumosides A and B. These compounds reduce stress and balance the neurotransmitters serotonin and dopamine in the brain.[5]Anti-inflammatory properties of Tulsi reduce inflammation and blood pressure.[6]

    Anti-cancer properties:

Phytochemicals present in Tulsi have strong antioxidant property. Thus, they help in protecting us from skin, liver, oral and lung cancers.[7]

    Good for Heart Health:

Tulsi has a profound effect on treatment and prevention of cardiovascular diseases by means of lowering blood lipid content, suppressing ischemia and stroke, reducing hypertension, and also due to its higher antioxidant properties.[8] Read more about tips for a healthy heart.

    Good for Diabetes Patients:

Extract of Tulsi leaves has shown to lower blood glucose levels in patients with type 2 Diabetes.[9]

    Useful in Kidney stones &amp; Gouty Arthritis:

Tulsi detoxifies the body and has diuretic properties. It decreases the level of uric acid in the body, which is the main reason why kidney stones are formed. Reduction in uric acid levels also provides relief to patients suffering from Gout.

    Useful in Gastrointestinal Disorders:

Tulsi leaves help to cure indigestion and loss of appetite. They are also used for the treatment of flatulence and bloating.

    Good for Skin &amp; Hair:

Tulsi helps clear out the skin of blemishes and acne. It is rich in antioxidants, and that helps it to prevent premature ageing. Tulsi also strengthens our hair roots, thus preventing hair loss.

Antifungal properties of Tulsi prevent the development of fungus and dandruff.



    Acts as an Insect Repellent:

For centuries, the dried Tulsi leaves have been mixed with stored grains to repel insects.
How to Consume Tulsi?

    Consume Tulsi leaves raw, plucked fresh from the plant, add it in your tea or make kadha out of it.
    Tulsi tea: To make tulsi tea, boil 1 cup of water and pour it over 1 tsp of fresh tulsi leaves, 1/2 tsp of dried tulsi leaves, or 1/3 tsp of tulsi powder. Cover the water in a pot or mug and let it seep for 15-20 minutes. Then strain the leaves, add honey if desired, and enjoy.
    Tulsi powders and supplements are also available in the market for consumption.

Side Effects of Consuming Tulsi That You Must Know:

    Tulsi may affect the reproductive capacity of women who are trying to conceive..
    Some people experience nausea or diarrhoea when they first add tulsi tea to their diet, so its best to start with small quantities and increase your consumption over time.
    Tulsi may lower blood sugar and should be used with caution in people who have diabetes and are on blood-sugar-lowering medication.
"</string>
    <string name="alovera_details">"Aloe vera is a popular medicinal plant that people have used for thousands of years.

Aloe vera, or Aloe barbadensis, is a thick, short-stemmed plant that stores water in its leaves. It is best known for treating skin injuries, but it also has several other uses that could potentially benefit health.

This article lists eight potential health benefits of aloe vera. It also covers some of the risks associated with use.\n\n

1. It contains healthful plant compounds
 The cosmetic, pharmaceutical, and food industries use aloe vera extensively, and the plant has an estimated annual market value of $13 billion globally.

Aloe vera is known for its thick, pointed, and fleshy green leaves, which may grow to about 12–19 inches (30–50 centimeters) in length.

Each leaf contains a slimy tissue that stores water, and this makes the leaves thick. This water filled tissue is the “gel” that people associate with aloe vera products.

The gel contains most of the beneficial bioactive compounds in the plant, including vitamins, minerals, amino acids, and antioxidants.


2. It has antioxidant and antibacterial properties

Antioxidants are important for health. Aloe vera gel contains powerful antioxidants belonging to a large family of substances known as polyphenols.

These polyphenols, along with several other compounds in aloe vera, help inhibit the growth of certain bacteria that can cause infections in humans.

Aloe vera is known for its antibacterial, antiviral, and antiseptic properties. This is part of why it may help heal wounds and treat skin problems.



3. It accelerates wound healing

People most often use aloe vera as a topical medication, rubbing it onto the skin rather than consuming it. In fact, it has a long history of use in treating sores, and particularly burns, including sunburn.

The United States Pharmacopeia describe aloe vera preparations as a skin protectant as early as 1810–1820.

Studies suggest that it is an effective topical treatment for first and second degree burns.

For example, a review of experimental studies found that aloe vera could reduce the healing time of burns by around 9 days compared with conventional medication. It also helped prevent redness, itching, and infections.

The evidence for aloe vera helping heal other types of wound is inconclusive, but the research is promising.


 4. It reduces dental plaque

Tooth decay and diseases of the gum are very common health problems. One of the best ways to prevent these conditions is to reduce the buildup of plaque, or bacterial biofilms, on the teeth.

In a mouth rinse study of 300 healthy people, researchers compared 100% pure aloe vera juice with the standard mouthwash ingredient chlorhexidine.

After 4 days of use, the aloe vera mouth rinse appeared to be just as effective as chlorhexidine in reducing dental plaque.

Another study found similar benefits of aloe vera mouth rinse over a 15- to 30-day period.

Aloe vera is effective in killing the plaque-producing bacterium Streptococcus mutans in the mouth, as well as the yeast Candida albicans.


5. It helps treat canker sores

Many people experience mouth ulcers, or canker sores, at some point in their lives. These usually form underneath the lip, inside the mouth, and last for about a week.

Studies have shown that aloe vera treatment can accelerate the healing of mouth ulcers.

For example, in a 7-day study of 180 people with recurrent mouth ulcers, applying an aloe vera patch to the area was effective in reducing the size of the ulcers.

However, it did not outperform the conventional ulcer treatment: corticosteroids.

In another study, aloe vera gel not only accelerated the healing of mouth ulcers, it also reduced the pain associated with them.


6. It reduces constipation

Aloe vera may also help treat constipation.

This time it is the latex, not the gel, that provides the benefits. The latex is a sticky yellow residue present just under the skin of the leaf.

The key compound responsible for this effect is called aloin, or barbaloin, which has well-established laxative effects.

However, people have raised concerns about safety with frequent use. For this reason, aloe latex has not been available in the U.S. as an over-the-counter medication since 2002.

Contrary to popular belief, aloe vera does not appear to be effective against other digestive conditions, such as irritable bowel syndrome or inflammatory bowel disease. Learn more here.\n\n


7. It may improve skin and prevent wrinkles

There is some preliminary evidence to suggest that topical aloe vera gel can slow aging of the skin.

In a 2009 study of 30 females over the age of 45, taking oral aloe vera gel increased collagen production and improved skin elasticity over a 90-day period.

Reviews also suggest that aloe vera could help the skin retain moisture and improve skin integrity, which could benefit dry skin conditions.



8. It lowers blood sugar levels

People sometimes use aloe vera as a remedy for diabetes. This is because it may enhance insulin sensitivity and help improve blood sugar management.

For example, a review of eight studies found that aloe vera could have benefits for people with prediabetes or type 2 diabetes due to its effects on glycemic control.

However, the quality of the existing studies is not ideal, so scientists do not currently recommend using aloe vera for this purpose.


Risks

Aloe vera is a safe remedy with few known side effects.

The National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) say that topical use is likely safe.

That said, the oral use of aloe vera may cause stomach cramps or diarrhea due to its laxative effects. There have also been some reports of liver damage associated with long-term aloe vera supplement use.

The NCCIH also report that nondecolorized whole leaf extract of aloe vera seems to be associated with cancer risk in rats.
Summary

Aloe vera has a range of therapeutic properties, especially as an ointment for the skin and gums.

People can use bottled aloe vera gel or take it directly from the leaf of an aloe plant. Aloe vera juice has different uses to aloe vera gel.

Oral options should contain decolorized whole leaf extract of aloe vera to minimize risk.

A person should always speak to a doctor before using aloe products to treat a condition."</string>

    <string name="title_activity_details">DetailsActivity</string>
    <string name="large_text">
        "Material is the metaphor.\n\n"

        "A material metaphor is the unifying theory of a rationalized space and a system of motion."
        "The material is grounded in tactile reality, inspired by the study of paper and ink, yet "
        "technologically advanced and open to imagination and magic.\n"
        "Surfaces and edges of the material provide visual cues that are grounded in reality. The "
        "use of familiar tactile attributes helps users quickly understand affordances. Yet the "
        "flexibility of the material creates new affordances that supercede those in the physical "
        "world, without breaking the rules of physics.\n"
        "The fundamentals of light, surface, and movement are key to conveying how objects move, "
        "interact, and exist in space and in relation to each other. Realistic lighting shows "
        "seams, divides space, and indicates moving parts.\n\n"

        "Bold, graphic, intentional.\n\n"

        "The foundational elements of print based design typography, grids, space, scale, color, "
        "and use of imagery guide visual treatments. These elements do far more than please the "
        "eye. They create hierarchy, meaning, and focus. Deliberate color choices, edge to edge "
        "imagery, large scale typography, and intentional white space create a bold and graphic "
        "interface that immerse the user in the experience.\n"
        "An emphasis on user actions makes core functionality immediately apparent and provides "
        "waypoints for the user.\n\n"

        "Motion provides meaning.\n\n"

        "Motion respects and reinforces the user as the prime mover. Primary user actions are "
        "inflection points that initiate motion, transforming the whole design.\n"
        "All action takes place in a single environment. Objects are presented to the user without "
        "breaking the continuity of experience even as they transform and reorganize.\n"
        "Motion is meaningful and appropriate, serving to focus attention and maintain continuity. "
        "Feedback is subtle yet clear. Transitions are efﬁcient yet coherent.\n\n"

        "3D world.\n\n"

        "The material environment is a 3D space, which means all objects have x, y, and z "
        "dimensions. The z-axis is perpendicularly aligned to the plane of the display, with the "
        "positive z-axis extending towards the viewer. Every sheet of material occupies a single "
        "position along the z-axis and has a standard 1dp thickness.\n"
        "On the web, the z-axis is used for layering and not for perspective. The 3D world is "
        "emulated by manipulating the y-axis.\n\n"

        "Light and shadow.\n\n"

        "Within the material environment, virtual lights illuminate the scene. Key lights create "
        "directional shadows, while ambient light creates soft shadows from all angles.\n"
        "Shadows in the material environment are cast by these two light sources. In Android "
        "development, shadows occur when light sources are blocked by sheets of material at "
        "various positions along the z-axis. On the web, shadows are depicted by manipulating the "
        "y-axis only. The following example shows the card with a height of 6dp.\n\n"

        "Resting elevation.\n\n"

        "All material objects, regardless of size, have a resting elevation, or default elevation "
        "that does not change. If an object changes elevation, it should return to its resting "
        "elevation as soon as possible.\n\n"

        "Component elevations.\n\n"

        "The resting elevation for a component type is consistent across apps (e.g., FAB elevation "
        "does not vary from 6dp in one app to 16dp in another app).\n"
        "Components may have different resting elevations across platforms, depending on the depth "
        "of the environment (e.g., TV has a greater depth than mobile or desktop).\n\n"

        "Responsive elevation and dynamic elevation offsets.\n\n"

        "Some component types have responsive elevation, meaning they change elevation in response "
        "to user input (e.g., normal, focused, and pressed) or system events. These elevation "
        "changes are consistently implemented using dynamic elevation offsets.\n"
        "Dynamic elevation offsets are the goal elevation that a component moves towards, relative "
        "to the component’s resting state. They ensure that elevation changes are consistent "
        "across actions and component types. For example, all components that lift on press have "
        "the same elevation change relative to their resting elevation.\n"
        "Once the input event is completed or cancelled, the component will return to its resting "
        "elevation.\n\n"

        "Avoiding elevation interference.\n\n"

        "Components with responsive elevations may encounter other components as they move between "
        "their resting elevations and dynamic elevation offsets. Because material cannot pass "
        "through other material, components avoid interfering with one another any number of ways, "
        "whether on a per component basis or using the entire app layout.\n"
        "On a component level, components can move or be removed before they cause interference. "
        "For example, a floating action button (FAB) can disappear or move off screen before a "
        "user picks up a card, or it can move if a snackbar appears.\n"
        "On the layout level, design your app layout to minimize opportunities for interference. "
        "For example, position the FAB to one side of stream of a cards so the FAB won’t interfere "
        "when a user tries to pick up one of cards.\n\n"

    </string>
    <!--Banner 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/6300978111
    Interstitial 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/1033173712
    Interstitial Video 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/8691691433
    Rewarded Video 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/5224354917
    Native Advanced 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/2247696110
    Native Advanced Video 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/1044960115-->

    <string name="app_id">ca-app-pub-3940256099942544~3347511713</string>
    <string name="banner_unit_id">ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/6300978111</string>
    <string name="interstitial_unit_id">ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/1033173712</string>

</resources>
