<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Ayurvedic</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="nav_header_title">Ayurvedic</string>
   <!-- <string name="nav_header_subtitle">android.studio@android.com</string>-->
    <string name="nav_header_desc">Navigation header</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Help</string>

    <string name="menu_home">Home</string>
    <string name="menu_gallery">Gallery</string>
    <string name="menu_slideshow">Slideshow</string>
    <string name="menu_tools">Tools</string>
    <string name="menu_share">Share</string>
    <string name="menu_send">Rate us</string>

    <string name="alovera">"ALovera \n\n What are the benefits of aloe vera?"</string>
    <string name="tusli">"Tusli \n\n The Health Benefits of Holy Basil"</string>
    <string name="triphala">"Top 20 Benefits of Triphala Churna (Powder)"</string>
    <string name="ashoka">"10 AMAZING Uses Of Ashoka Tree Will Leave You Shellshocked!"</string>
    <string name="ashoka_details">"The beautiful ashoka tree has many gifts to offer us. From improving complexion to relieving pain, the tree is versatile. There is so much to know about this woman-friendly tree.

Why do you think I said woman-friendly? Read on and find out.


    Table Of Contents

    About Ashoka Tree
    Why The Tree Is Woman Friendly
    Benefits of Ashoka Tree


About Ashoka Tree

Primarily a rainforest tree, the Ashoka has luscious foliage and beautiful orange-yellow flowers. The flower bunches are bright, heavy and fragrant. The tree is found in the Indian subcontinent, particularly close to the foothills of the Himalayas as well as the Western Ghats.

Ashoka tree is considered sacred throughout Nepal, India, and Sri Lanka. It has strong religious associations, with Buddhists and Hindus including the tree in their cultural traditions. Ashoka tree finds prominence in ancient Hindu mythology, art, sculpture and even Ramayana. It is said that Buddha was born under an Ashoka tree.


Why The Tree Is Woman Friendly

I called the Ashoka tree a woman’s friend because of its reputation to keep a woman youthful. Apparently, the tree can drive away a woman’s pain and sorrow through its ability to gift good health. Incidentally, the word Ashoka is translated as ‘no grief’ or ‘without sorrow’ in Sanskrit.

The tree has many medicinal qualities (1). Needless to say, dried stem, bark and flowers from the tree find applications in many areas. Tonics and capsules made from seeds, flowers, and bark, are widely used in India for treating a variety of health conditions.



Female Reproductive Health


Menstrual Problems

As an effective uterine tonic, Ashoka is hard to beat. It tones the uterus, easing heavy menstrual flow and relieving discomfort. The bark of the Ashoka tree is rich in flavonoids, tannins and glycosides that work as a uterine sedative that has a direct impact on the fibres present in the muscles of the uterus.

The bark also contains natural phytoestrogens which help to regulate the menstrual cycle, stimulating the uterus to normalise menstrual flow.

Ashoka can be effectively used to aid with a number of uncomfortable menstrual disorders such as; Premenstrual Syndrome (PMS), Amenorrhea (absent periods), Dysmenorrhea (painful periods) and Menorrhagia (heavy and prolonged menstrual bleeding).


Menopause

Recent studies have confirmed the presence of quercetin, beta-sitosterol and luteolin, phytoestrogens that support healthy hormonal function during the transition into the menopause. One particular study found that the bark exerts a balancing effect on artificially elevated oestrogen levels, exhibiting adaptogenic qualities that are referred to in Ayurveda as “herbal intelligence”. Furthermore, it can support the healthy production of oestrogen and progesterone only when it is needed.

The hormonal balance that is promoted by this herb makes it effective against many menopause symptoms including; hot flushes, night sweats, sleep problems, mood swings and weight gain.


Infertility

Ashoka is considered particularly effective for female infertility and endometriosis. One study, published in "Complementary Therapies in Clinical Practice", identified Ashoka as one of the herbal remedies used by traditional healers in remote areas of India to successfully treat “reproductive disorders”.

An article published in the "Journal of Clinical and Diagnostic Research", explored some of the infertility treatments popular amongst Indian women. It said, “The drug of choice for female infertility is Ashoka, by its astringent taste and cold potency, it strengthens the uterus. It stops the bleeding by contracting the uterine blood vessels and promoting uterine muscular contraction. It stimulates the uterine function by stimulating the (endometrium) and the ovarian functions”.

It is important to note that diet and lifestyle were also addressed during treatment. The success of Ashoka in the treatment of infertility in women may be linked to the herb’s ability to successfully treat endometrios - one of the leading causes of infertility in women.


Benefits of Ashoka Tree

1. Gynecological Problems

Ashoka tree is popularly used in the treatment of gynecological problems and menstrual disorders in women. The herb acts as a tonic for uterine muscles and endometrium, controlling spasms and abdominal pain.

It is taken to treat and alleviate symptoms of irregular menstrual cycles, dysmenorrhoea, amenorrhoea, leucorrhoea, fibroids, cysts and other related disorders.



2. Skin Complexion

The Ashoka herb can naturally improve the skin’s complexion. It helps in blood purification and prevention of further skin allergies. As it removes toxins, it serves to clear the complexion. Moreover, extracts from the tree can also be used to soothe burns and skin irritations.


3. Pain Relief

Ashoka tree has pain relieving properties and can be used as an analgesic safely. Use the paste of the bark for joint pains and experience relief.


4. Internal Bleeding

The herb can treat internal bleeding and hemorrhages effectively. The Ashoka flower extract is used to treat hemorrhagic dysentery. Drink a few drops of water mixed with crushed Ashoka flower for treating the condition.


5. Diabetes

Similarly, dried flowers from Ashoka tree are helpful for diabetics. Consume tonics or decoctions regularly to benefit from the tree’s offerings.


6. Piles

Ashoka tree extracts are used in the treatment of internal piles and bleeding due to piles. The herbal supplements, prepared from the bark, are made into decoctions and consumed.


7. Infections

Ward away fungal and bacterial infections with the tree’s bark. The bark is composed of properties that purify the body and eliminate infections.


8. Worms

This herb can treat worm infections as well. Clear your stomach of worm infestations by consuming leaves or bark of the Ashoka tree. It not only relieves pain, but also reduces bloating.


9. Diarrhea

Ashoka tree and its offerings will treat your diarrhea without any side effects. Use the Ashoka tree leaves, flowers and bark as a tonic and feel the relief. It also purifies the blood in the process.


10. Kidney Stones

Ashoka tree seed power is a natural method to control kidney stones. Have the powder with water, which will decrease your risk of painful stone extraction.

The tree is revered for its healing properties. However, it has only one contraindication. Ashoka tree extracts are not meant for consumption by pregnant women as they are abortive in nature.


"</string>
    <string name="triphala_details">"India is the land of Ayurveda, and people truly believe in the power of herbal preparations in treating various medical conditions. Since time immemorial, Triphala, better known as Triphala churna, has proven its efficacy in treating various health ailments. With people becoming more aware of the cons of modern-day allopathic medicines, herbal preparations are gaining popularity, and people are opting for these herbal preparations to feel better. Here is how you can benefit by taking this herbal remedy.


        What is Triphala Churna?

Triphala means three fruits. Therefore, Triphala churna is not made of one single herbal ingredient, but a combination of three fruits. The three fruits include Haritaki or Terminalia chebula, Bibhitaki or Terminalia bellirica, and Amla or Emblica Officinalis. These fruits are completely dried, powdered and then mixed in the correct amounts to make the Triphala churna.

        What are the Benefits of Triphala Churna?

Some of the many benefits of Triphala powder include:


1. Helpful in Weight Loss

Excess weight is one of the most dreaded health demons and also the foundation of many other health problems. If you are looking for easier ways to keep your weight under check, Triphala may help you in achieving that. Taking Triphala churna aids the secretion of cholecystokinin in the body. Cholecystokinin is a hormone that is helpful in quickly signalling the brain that the stomach is full. This makes you feel fuller and also help you feel satiated. You can take a tablespoon of this churna three times a day with warm water to protect yourself from obesity issues. It is also effective in reducing excess belly fat.


2. Acts as a Detoxifier

The toxins in our body keep piling up as we keep eating unhealthy food items, and these toxins are responsible for making us sick. Therefore, it is important to detoxify our body and get rid of these harmful toxins. Triphala can be used to avail this health benefit too. This churna not only helps in getting rid of all the deadly toxins from your body but is also good for your skin by making it glow. You can make a decoction by mixing a tablespoon of this powder in a glass of water. Add crushed ginger and boil the decoction until it is reduced to half. Strain the decoction and add lemon juice. Drink when warm for maximum benefits. Ideally, this decoction should be had on an empty stomach; you may take this for at least a week to help your body get rid of the toxins.


3. Cures Digestive Issues

If you are dealing with any kind of digestive issues, you can consume Triphala to feel better. This churna not only helps in easing the bowel movements but also regulates the bowel movements due to its laxative properties. If you’re feeling bloated, your tummy is feeling heavy, or you have loose motions, you can safely consume this powder in the morning with lots of water. This churna also takes care of your digestive health by strengthening rectal muscles, relieving flatulence and keeping the stomach clean.


4. Helps in Fighting Infections and Enhances Immunity

Consuming this powdered medicine is a great way of enhancing your immunity. The combination of three fruits is an effective herbal medicine in improving one’s immunity, thus protecting the body against infections that may be caused due to Staphylococcus bacteria, E.Coli etc. By aiding the blood circulation and nourishing the body with essential nutrients, Triphala helps the body in building a better immune system, which is also effective in protecting the body from various infections.


5. Beneficial in Maintaining Oral Hygiene

Many of us might suffer from dental issues such as dental plaque, gingivitis, gum diseases, mouth ulcers and other such dental disorders. This herbal powder is loaded with antimicrobial properties. In a study, it has been proven that a mouth rinse with Triphala extracts showed effective results in dealing with dental issues such as gingivitis and plaque. Also, in a study, it was established that Triphala churna was better in dealing with gum issues in comparison other commercial toothpaste.


6. Beneficial for Eye Health

This herbal remedy is a boon for the eyes and can be aptly called the tonic for maintaining good eye health. It not only helps in keeping your eyes healthy but it also aids in maintaining a sharp vision. Triphala is also effective in keeping various eye troubles or infections such as glaucoma, conjunctivitis, cataract etc. at bay. You may consume the churna orally, or you may use it as an eyewash to help soothe the eye infection. People who spend more time in front of their computer screens, phones or other such electronics may suffer from a condition known as ‘computer vision syndrome’. In a study, it has been proven that Triphala eye drops helped in reducing the symptoms of computer vision syndrome. You may soak 1 to 2 teaspoons of this churna in warm water and let it sit overnight. In the morning, you may strain the water and wash your eyes with this water.


7. Helpful in Treating Gastric Ulcers

Triphala is also beneficial in treating gastric ulcers. This is because when this churna is taken on a regular basis, it reduces the internal as well as external inflammation. It also helps in restoring the enzymes in the body that keeps the toxins away from the body and helps in strengthening the mucous membrane of the stomach.


8. Helps in Treating Urinary Tract Infections

UTI or urinary tract infection can affect both men and women. This painful condition may sometimes become hard to cure, especially when the bacteria causing the infection become immune to the antibiotic medicines or do not respond well to the conventional methods of treatment. During such situations, you may consider using Triphala churna to cure the urinary tract infection. This herbal combination is not only safe and has no side-effects, but it is also has shown promising results on various drug-resistant bacteria.


9. Helpful in Reducing Joint and Bone Pains

If you are suffering from bone or joint pain, Triphala may offer the solution to your problem. This churna is effective in maintaining good bone health by providing ample nutrients to the body. It also aids flushing of excessive amounts of uric acid from the body, which is responsible for bone and joint inflammation. Whenever you experience a joint or bone pain such as gout, arthritis, joint pain etc., you may mix a teaspoon of this powder in some warm water and take this decoction to ease your pain.


10. Helpful in Healing Wounds

The churna has anti-microbial and anti-inflammatory properties, and thus this herbal remedy works wonders in healing various wounds and also aids the recovery process.


11. Effective in Regulating Blood Pressure

Irregular blood pressure may lead to various kinds of health troubles. However, consuming Triphala on a regular basis is beneficial in regulating your blood pressure levels and thus keeping off various health troubles.


12. Helpful in Stimulating Hair Growth

There are many benefits of Triphala churna for hair, and one of the benefits includes stimulating hair growth. Therefore, if you are battling growth issues with your hair, Triphala may be your one-stop solution. You can either consume this herbal remedy orally or make a paste with this churna by adding some water and then applying it on your hair. Triphala is loaded with emollient properties, which are helpful in locking the moisture and thus preventing alopecia. The topical application or oral consumption, both help in aiding the hair growth.


13. Keeps Your Hormones in Place

It is very important to have a healthy hormonal balance in the body because any kind of hormonal imbalance may lead to health complications. Therefore, if you are experiencing painful periods or irregular periods, consuming Triphala churna may prove to be beneficial in providing a remedy to your problem. You may consume a teaspoonful of this churna with a glass of warm water before retiring for the night or two hours after your dinner to regulate your hormonal balance.


14. Helpful in Reducing Dark Circles

Are you fighting dark circles under your eyes? Well, gone are the days when panda eyes were something that you had to live with because now you have Triphala to the rescue. Puffy eyes, dark circles, tired eyes and other such under-eye issues can get cured by using Triphala. You can take eyewash made with Triphala. This not only reduces dark circles and puffiness but it also helps in keeping good eye health.


15. Helpful in Curing Bad Breath

Bad or foul breath can be a big turn off and make you feel embarrassed too. Say no to bad breath with this miraculous churna. You can add honey to the churna and lick this mixture for warding off bad breath. On the other hand, you can also gargle with water in which a teaspoon of powder is mixed to keep bad breath at bay.


16. Beneficial for Kids

Triphala churna not only offers ample benefits for the adults but it also renders many benefits to the children. Young children do not have a very strong immunity, and thus this churna is not only good to improve the immunity in children, but it is also effective in fighting various kinds of common infections that kids usually suffer from such as a cough, cold, fever etc. You may give Triphala with milk, water or mixed with some honey. If your baby is less than 12 months, you should not give more than a pinch of this churna. For older kids, a teaspoon may be given.



17. Helpful in Motion Sickness and Curing Dizziness

Many of us may be dreading travelling because of the sheer thought of motion sickness. However, taking this churna may help you overcome your dizziness or motion sickness. Every time you feel sick, you may take a few grams of this churna mixed with honey to feel better. On the other hand, if you experience any kind of dizziness on a regular basis, you may take this mixture every day in the morning.


18. Helpful in Managing Diabetes

If you are suffering from diabetes, you may take Triphala to manage your blood sugar levels. This is an alternative treatment method that makes use of herbal remedies in balancing the sugar in the blood. This remedy not only regulates the sugar but it also aids in bringing it down and thus works as an effective treatment for managing diabetes.


19. Helpful in Boosting Heart Health

Triphala acts as a tonic for your heart because it helps in improving or boosting heart health. This happens because by consuming this churna your blood circulation improves, your bad cholesterol goes down and your blood pressure gets regulated. Together all these factors help in improving the overall heart health and thus keeping the heart healthy. Therefore, in order to have good cardio health, you may like to give Triphala a try.



20. Helps in Skin Rejuvenation

Looking for baby soft and smooth skin? If yes, then look no further and opt for Triphala for a healthy skin glow and to obtain that unbeatable freshness. This churna has antioxidants in it, which helps in fighting various skin infections and also reduces acne-causing bacteria. If you have dry or flaky skin, you can benefit greatly by using Triphala because it has ample amounts of emollient properties that helps in keeping the skin soft and moist.

The above-mentioned are some of the many benefits of consuming Triphala.


How to Make Triphala Powder at Home?

Why procure the churna from the market when you can safely make it at home. All you have to do is procure the right ingredients. Here is what you need and what you should do to make a perfect Triphala churna.



Ingredients:

To make this ayurvedic remedy, you require:

    Amla- 80 grams
    Baheda- 40 grams
    Harad- 20 grams
    Mortar and pestle

Method:

The method of making this churna is very simple and easy.

    Take all the ingredients in the right amounts and dry them completely.
    Once all the ingredients are dried up, take them one by one and ground them into a fine powder using mortar and pestle.
    Sieve the powder and mix all the powdered ingredients well.
    Store them in an airtight container.


Ways to Take Triphala Churna for Best Results

Some of the benefits of this churna were given in the above section, and now we shall explain how you should take this churna for the best results:


1. Take It In a Form of Tea

You may have tea made from this powder and drink it to feel hale and hearty. You can take a teaspoon of this churna and boil in water. Strain and add honey for some taste. You may safely consume this tea two to three times a day.

2. Triphala Face Pack

Now achieving a blemish-free glowing skin is not that difficult. All you need to do is use Triphala to feel radiant. You can take a spoonful of this powder and mix it nicely with some coconut oil. Apply liberally over your face and neck. Leave this pack for approximately 10 to 15 minutes and then rinse off with warm water. Your skin will be soft, supple and with regular use, it will also become blemish-free.

3. Triphala Eyewash

As stated above, Triphala is beneficial in keeping your eyes beautiful and healthy. You can also make eyewash using this churna. All you have to do it mix this powder in a glass of water and leave it overnight. In the morning, you can strain and use the water for washing your eyes to keep them healthy and safe from any kinds of infections.

4. Triphala with Lemon and Honey

Some people may find it difficult to gulp down Triphala because of this strange taste. For those of you who face issues in consuming it in powdered form, you may mix lemon juice and honey to make it palatable. However, ideally, you should consume the churna with warm water without any additives to avail the maximum benefits. Alternatively, you may also avail benefits of Triphala churna by taking it with milk.

5. Triphala In The Form Of Capsules And Tablets

Another option for people who cannot consume it in a powdered form is to take this herbal preparation in the form of tablets or capsules. There are many renowned herbal brands that make such capsules and tablets. Also, it is easier to consume Triphala in this form. However, ensure that you do not consume it is large amounts or else it may lead to complications.
Warning

Triphala churna is one of the safest ayurvedic remedies that have been in use for a long time. However, there are certain considerations you must exercise for achieving the most from this herbal remedy. Here are certain precautionary measures that you should consider before taking this herbal preparation:

    Though Triphala is good for people suffering from diabetes, however, it is suggested that you consult your doctor before taking this herbal remedy on a regular basis.

    Refrain from taking more than the recommended dosage or as prescribed by your doctor. More than required amounts may lead to dehydration.

    Babies may also benefit from this herbal remedy, but you should not give them more than a pinch of this powder. This is because more amounts of Triphala may make your baby’s tummy upset and cause diarrhoea or other tummy issues.

    This churna is loaded with fibre, and if more than required amount is consumed, it may lead to bloating. Also, you should take smaller dosages of this churna if you are suffering from gastric issues.

    A pregnant and breastfeeding mother should not take this herbal remedy. This is because Triphala may cause downward energy flow, which may lead to natural abortion or miscarriage. This herbal medicine can also pass through the breast milk to the baby; therefore, breastfeeding mothers should avoid taking it.


FAQs

Here are some commonly or frequently asked questions about consuming Triphala churna:

1. Can Triphala Churna Interact with Medications?

Whenever you are taking Triphala, you must ensure that there is at least a gap of 12 hours before you take any other medication. If you do not follow this gap, there are chances that this churna interacts with your other medications. The best way to clear confusion is to consult your doctor and ask how you can take your medication if you are taking this churna too.

2. Is there an Effective Time to Take Triphala Churna?

No, there is no particular time or for that matter season when you should consume this churna. You should consume this herbal medicine on a regular basis to avail maximum benefits. However, the best way to take this churna is on an empty stomach with some warm water. Alternatively, this churna can be had two hours before bedtime with some warm water. The best way to get the optimum benefits is by consuming this herbal preparation in the prescribed amounts.

Ayurveda is flooded with many effective herbal medicines that can be used to cure many health problems. You can safely consume this remedy and bid goodbye to some of your serious medical issues. However, it is suggested that you consult an ayurvedic doctor before taking this herbal remedy.

"</string>
    <string name="tulsi_details">"Tulsi or Holy basil is a widely known herb in the family Lamiaceae. It is native to India and vastly cultivated throughout Southeast Asia.

Tulsi has proved to be highly effective in protecting our body from various infections and diseases of heart, liver, skin, kidney etc. [1]So, Tulsi is rightly called the ‘Queen of Herbs’.

Tulsi has a special place in Ayurveda as well as the home of Hindus in India. It is considered sacred by Hindus and worshipped by them. Three main types of Tulsi are seen growing in India:

    Bright green leaves called Ram Tulsi
    Purplish green leaves called Krishna Tulsi
    Common wild Vana Tulsi.

Nutritional Value:

Tulsi leaves are rich in vitamins A, C and K and minerals like calcium, magnesium, phosphorus, iron and potassium. It also has a good amount of protein and fibre.
11 Research-Backed Benefits of Tulsi are:

    Natural Immunity Booster:

Tulsi is rich in Vitamin C and zinc. It thus acts as a natural immunity booster and keeps infections at bay. It has immense anti-bacterial, anti-viral and anti-fungal properties which protect us from a variety of infections. Tulsi leaves extract increases the T helper cells and natural killer cells activity, boosting the immune system.[2]

Also Read: 7 Tips to Boost Immunity.

    Reduces Fever (antipyretic) &amp; Pain(analgesic):

Tulsi has anti-bacterial and anti-viral properties which help to fight infections, thus reducing fever. The fresh juice of Tulsi taken with black pepper powder cures periodic fevers. Tulsi leaves boiled with powdered cardamom(elaichi) in half a litre of water and mixed with sugar and milk, is also effective in reducing temperature. [3]

Eugenol, a terpene with pain-relieving properties found in Tulsi reduces aches in the body.

    Reduces Cold, Cough &amp; Other Respiratory Disorders:

Camphene, cineole, and eugenol present in Tulsi helps to reduce cold and congestion in the chest.

Juice of Tulsi leaves mixed with honey and ginger is effective in bronchitis, asthma, influenza, cough and cold.[4]

    Reduces Stress &amp; Blood Pressure:

Tulsi contains compounds Ocimumosides A and B. These compounds reduce stress and balance the neurotransmitters serotonin and dopamine in the brain.[5]Anti-inflammatory properties of Tulsi reduce inflammation and blood pressure.[6]

    Anti-cancer properties:

Phytochemicals present in Tulsi have strong antioxidant property. Thus, they help in protecting us from skin, liver, oral and lung cancers.[7]

    Good for Heart Health:

Tulsi has a profound effect on treatment and prevention of cardiovascular diseases by means of lowering blood lipid content, suppressing ischemia and stroke, reducing hypertension, and also due to its higher antioxidant properties.[8] Read more about tips for a healthy heart.

    Good for Diabetes Patients:

Extract of Tulsi leaves has shown to lower blood glucose levels in patients with type 2 Diabetes.[9]

    Useful in Kidney stones &amp; Gouty Arthritis:

Tulsi detoxifies the body and has diuretic properties. It decreases the level of uric acid in the body, which is the main reason why kidney stones are formed. Reduction in uric acid levels also provides relief to patients suffering from Gout.

    Useful in Gastrointestinal Disorders:

Tulsi leaves help to cure indigestion and loss of appetite. They are also used for the treatment of flatulence and bloating.

    Good for Skin &amp; Hair:

Tulsi helps clear out the skin of blemishes and acne. It is rich in antioxidants, and that helps it to prevent premature ageing. Tulsi also strengthens our hair roots, thus preventing hair loss.

Antifungal properties of Tulsi prevent the development of fungus and dandruff.



    Acts as an Insect Repellent:

For centuries, the dried Tulsi leaves have been mixed with stored grains to repel insects.
How to Consume Tulsi?

    Consume Tulsi leaves raw, plucked fresh from the plant, add it in your tea or make kadha out of it.
    Tulsi tea: To make tulsi tea, boil 1 cup of water and pour it over 1 tsp of fresh tulsi leaves, 1/2 tsp of dried tulsi leaves, or 1/3 tsp of tulsi powder. Cover the water in a pot or mug and let it seep for 15-20 minutes. Then strain the leaves, add honey if desired, and enjoy.
    Tulsi powders and supplements are also available in the market for consumption.

Side Effects of Consuming Tulsi That You Must Know:

    Tulsi may affect the reproductive capacity of women who are trying to conceive..
    Some people experience nausea or diarrhoea when they first add tulsi tea to their diet, so its best to start with small quantities and increase your consumption over time.
    Tulsi may lower blood sugar and should be used with caution in people who have diabetes and are on blood-sugar-lowering medication.
"</string>
    <string name="alovera_details">"Aloe vera is a popular medicinal plant that people have used for thousands of years.

Aloe vera, or Aloe barbadensis, is a thick, short-stemmed plant that stores water in its leaves. It is best known for treating skin injuries, but it also has several other uses that could potentially benefit health.

This article lists eight potential health benefits of aloe vera. It also covers some of the risks associated with use.\n\n

1. It contains healthful plant compounds
 The cosmetic, pharmaceutical, and food industries use aloe vera extensively, and the plant has an estimated annual market value of $13 billion globally.

Aloe vera is known for its thick, pointed, and fleshy green leaves, which may grow to about 12–19 inches (30–50 centimeters) in length.

Each leaf contains a slimy tissue that stores water, and this makes the leaves thick. This water filled tissue is the “gel” that people associate with aloe vera products.

The gel contains most of the beneficial bioactive compounds in the plant, including vitamins, minerals, amino acids, and antioxidants.


2. It has antioxidant and antibacterial properties

Antioxidants are important for health. Aloe vera gel contains powerful antioxidants belonging to a large family of substances known as polyphenols.

These polyphenols, along with several other compounds in aloe vera, help inhibit the growth of certain bacteria that can cause infections in humans.

Aloe vera is known for its antibacterial, antiviral, and antiseptic properties. This is part of why it may help heal wounds and treat skin problems.



3. It accelerates wound healing

People most often use aloe vera as a topical medication, rubbing it onto the skin rather than consuming it. In fact, it has a long history of use in treating sores, and particularly burns, including sunburn.

The United States Pharmacopeia describe aloe vera preparations as a skin protectant as early as 1810–1820.

Studies suggest that it is an effective topical treatment for first and second degree burns.

For example, a review of experimental studies found that aloe vera could reduce the healing time of burns by around 9 days compared with conventional medication. It also helped prevent redness, itching, and infections.

The evidence for aloe vera helping heal other types of wound is inconclusive, but the research is promising.


 4. It reduces dental plaque

Tooth decay and diseases of the gum are very common health problems. One of the best ways to prevent these conditions is to reduce the buildup of plaque, or bacterial biofilms, on the teeth.

In a mouth rinse study of 300 healthy people, researchers compared 100% pure aloe vera juice with the standard mouthwash ingredient chlorhexidine.

After 4 days of use, the aloe vera mouth rinse appeared to be just as effective as chlorhexidine in reducing dental plaque.

Another study found similar benefits of aloe vera mouth rinse over a 15- to 30-day period.

Aloe vera is effective in killing the plaque-producing bacterium Streptococcus mutans in the mouth, as well as the yeast Candida albicans.


5. It helps treat canker sores

Many people experience mouth ulcers, or canker sores, at some point in their lives. These usually form underneath the lip, inside the mouth, and last for about a week.

Studies have shown that aloe vera treatment can accelerate the healing of mouth ulcers.

For example, in a 7-day study of 180 people with recurrent mouth ulcers, applying an aloe vera patch to the area was effective in reducing the size of the ulcers.

However, it did not outperform the conventional ulcer treatment: corticosteroids.

In another study, aloe vera gel not only accelerated the healing of mouth ulcers, it also reduced the pain associated with them.


6. It reduces constipation

Aloe vera may also help treat constipation.

This time it is the latex, not the gel, that provides the benefits. The latex is a sticky yellow residue present just under the skin of the leaf.

The key compound responsible for this effect is called aloin, or barbaloin, which has well-established laxative effects.

However, people have raised concerns about safety with frequent use. For this reason, aloe latex has not been available in the U.S. as an over-the-counter medication since 2002.

Contrary to popular belief, aloe vera does not appear to be effective against other digestive conditions, such as irritable bowel syndrome or inflammatory bowel disease. Learn more here.\n\n


7. It may improve skin and prevent wrinkles

There is some preliminary evidence to suggest that topical aloe vera gel can slow aging of the skin.

In a 2009 study of 30 females over the age of 45, taking oral aloe vera gel increased collagen production and improved skin elasticity over a 90-day period.

Reviews also suggest that aloe vera could help the skin retain moisture and improve skin integrity, which could benefit dry skin conditions.



8. It lowers blood sugar levels

People sometimes use aloe vera as a remedy for diabetes. This is because it may enhance insulin sensitivity and help improve blood sugar management.

For example, a review of eight studies found that aloe vera could have benefits for people with prediabetes or type 2 diabetes due to its effects on glycemic control.

However, the quality of the existing studies is not ideal, so scientists do not currently recommend using aloe vera for this purpose.


Risks

Aloe vera is a safe remedy with few known side effects.

The National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH) say that topical use is likely safe.

That said, the oral use of aloe vera may cause stomach cramps or diarrhea due to its laxative effects. There have also been some reports of liver damage associated with long-term aloe vera supplement use.

The NCCIH also report that nondecolorized whole leaf extract of aloe vera seems to be associated with cancer risk in rats.
Summary

Aloe vera has a range of therapeutic properties, especially as an ointment for the skin and gums.

People can use bottled aloe vera gel or take it directly from the leaf of an aloe plant. Aloe vera juice has different uses to aloe vera gel.

Oral options should contain decolorized whole leaf extract of aloe vera to minimize risk.

A person should always speak to a doctor before using aloe products to treat a condition."</string>

    <string name="title_activity_details">DetailsActivity</string>
    <string name="large_text">
        "Material is the metaphor.\n\n"

        "A material metaphor is the unifying theory of a rationalized space and a system of motion."
        "The material is grounded in tactile reality, inspired by the study of paper and ink, yet "
        "technologically advanced and open to imagination and magic.\n"
        "Surfaces and edges of the material provide visual cues that are grounded in reality. The "
        "use of familiar tactile attributes helps users quickly understand affordances. Yet the "
        "flexibility of the material creates new affordances that supercede those in the physical "
        "world, without breaking the rules of physics.\n"
        "The fundamentals of light, surface, and movement are key to conveying how objects move, "
        "interact, and exist in space and in relation to each other. Realistic lighting shows "
        "seams, divides space, and indicates moving parts.\n\n"

        "Bold, graphic, intentional.\n\n"

        "The foundational elements of print based design typography, grids, space, scale, color, "
        "and use of imagery guide visual treatments. These elements do far more than please the "
        "eye. They create hierarchy, meaning, and focus. Deliberate color choices, edge to edge "
        "imagery, large scale typography, and intentional white space create a bold and graphic "
        "interface that immerse the user in the experience.\n"
        "An emphasis on user actions makes core functionality immediately apparent and provides "
        "waypoints for the user.\n\n"

        "Motion provides meaning.\n\n"

        "Motion respects and reinforces the user as the prime mover. Primary user actions are "
        "inflection points that initiate motion, transforming the whole design.\n"
        "All action takes place in a single environment. Objects are presented to the user without "
        "breaking the continuity of experience even as they transform and reorganize.\n"
        "Motion is meaningful and appropriate, serving to focus attention and maintain continuity. "
        "Feedback is subtle yet clear. Transitions are efﬁcient yet coherent.\n\n"

        "3D world.\n\n"

        "The material environment is a 3D space, which means all objects have x, y, and z "
        "dimensions. The z-axis is perpendicularly aligned to the plane of the display, with the "
        "positive z-axis extending towards the viewer. Every sheet of material occupies a single "
        "position along the z-axis and has a standard 1dp thickness.\n"
        "On the web, the z-axis is used for layering and not for perspective. The 3D world is "
        "emulated by manipulating the y-axis.\n\n"

        "Light and shadow.\n\n"

        "Within the material environment, virtual lights illuminate the scene. Key lights create "
        "directional shadows, while ambient light creates soft shadows from all angles.\n"
        "Shadows in the material environment are cast by these two light sources. In Android "
        "development, shadows occur when light sources are blocked by sheets of material at "
        "various positions along the z-axis. On the web, shadows are depicted by manipulating the "
        "y-axis only. The following example shows the card with a height of 6dp.\n\n"

        "Resting elevation.\n\n"

        "All material objects, regardless of size, have a resting elevation, or default elevation "
        "that does not change. If an object changes elevation, it should return to its resting "
        "elevation as soon as possible.\n\n"

        "Component elevations.\n\n"

        "The resting elevation for a component type is consistent across apps (e.g., FAB elevation "
        "does not vary from 6dp in one app to 16dp in another app).\n"
        "Components may have different resting elevations across platforms, depending on the depth "
        "of the environment (e.g., TV has a greater depth than mobile or desktop).\n\n"

        "Responsive elevation and dynamic elevation offsets.\n\n"

        "Some component types have responsive elevation, meaning they change elevation in response "
        "to user input (e.g., normal, focused, and pressed) or system events. These elevation "
        "changes are consistently implemented using dynamic elevation offsets.\n"
        "Dynamic elevation offsets are the goal elevation that a component moves towards, relative "
        "to the component’s resting state. They ensure that elevation changes are consistent "
        "across actions and component types. For example, all components that lift on press have "
        "the same elevation change relative to their resting elevation.\n"
        "Once the input event is completed or cancelled, the component will return to its resting "
        "elevation.\n\n"

        "Avoiding elevation interference.\n\n"

        "Components with responsive elevations may encounter other components as they move between "
        "their resting elevations and dynamic elevation offsets. Because material cannot pass "
        "through other material, components avoid interfering with one another any number of ways, "
        "whether on a per component basis or using the entire app layout.\n"
        "On a component level, components can move or be removed before they cause interference. "
        "For example, a floating action button (FAB) can disappear or move off screen before a "
        "user picks up a card, or it can move if a snackbar appears.\n"
        "On the layout level, design your app layout to minimize opportunities for interference. "
        "For example, position the FAB to one side of stream of a cards so the FAB won’t interfere "
        "when a user tries to pick up one of cards.\n\n"

    </string>
    <!--Banner 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/6300978111
    Interstitial 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/1033173712
    Interstitial Video 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/8691691433
    Rewarded Video 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/5224354917
    Native Advanced 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/2247696110
    Native Advanced Video 	ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/1044960115-->

    <string name="app_id">ca-app-pub-3940256099942544~3347511713</string>
    <string name="banner_unit_id">ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/6300978111</string>
    <string name="interstitial_unit_id">ca-app-pub-3940256099942544/1033173712</string>

</resources>
